Hello and welcome to Section 5 web servers and application deployment we're covering a ton of exciting
stuff in this section.
You're going to learn how to make a web server.
You're going to learn how to integrate a version control into node applications.
And finally you're going to learn how to deploy your node apps which means that you have a you are Alan
anyone who visits that you r l can view your application.
Now do you get all that done we are going to be looking at a framework called Express.
It's one of the most popular NPM libraries and for good reason it makes it really easy to do stuff like
create a web server or an h t t p API.
Kind of like the dark sky API we used in the last section.
Now most courses start here.
They start with Express and I think that's confusing because it blurs the line between what is node
and what is Express which is why we've waited so long to talk about it.
Don't get me wrong it's a fantastic library but I wanted to wait a little bit to introduce it now that
I am introducing it.
So let's go ahead and kick things off.
Adding express to a brand new node app