In this video Your challenge is going to be to go through the entire development lifecycle from having
an idea to deploying it.
You're going to create the code locally.
You'll be testing it locally then you're going to make a commit push it up to get hub and finally deploy
it to Heroku where it'll be visible live on the web.
That is the entire process.
I want you to run through now whether you're using get hub in a Roku or other services the process is
still really similar.
So it's a good idea to get comfortable going through this process early on as it's something you'll
be doing when you're adding new features.
Your challenge is going to be to add a new projects page to our Web site.
This page is a place where later on you can link to your get have projects.
That means you're going to need to register a new you are all down below and we're going to be rendering
a handlebars template you off to create that you are.
It's going to be a forward slash projects.
You also need to make that view file and in the view file kind of like we do for home and about.
I want you to render everything including the header and footer and inside of the actual Web site you
can just render a message like Portfolio page here inside of the Parshall's header file.
I also want you to add a new link for the new projects page.
So when you're on the home page you can go to projects and when you're on the projects page you can
go to home or about wherever you like.
Now once you're done and you have tested this locally meaning you've opened it up on localhost three
thousand and you can see the projects page you're ready to make that comment go ahead and make that
commit then push it up to get hub.
The last step in the process is going to be to push it up to that Heroku remote using get Pusch Heroku
which is going to deploy it live to the web.
Once you're done you can open up your app inside of the browser and I want you to check to make sure
the project's page shows up as expected.
We've gone through all these steps before but take your time.
There is no rush.
Once you have things ready you can go ahead and click play
how to go.
Hopefully you are able to go through that entire process without too much trouble.
We're going to get started by creating the local changes that means I'm going to register a new u r
l right here using app dot get we're going to create a new page of forward slash projects which is why
I have that as the route for my HTP get handler inside of the second argument we can specify our callback
function which we'll get called with request and response and like we do for the other routes above
the route route and are about route we're going to be calling response dot render to render our template
inside of the render arguments list.
We're going to provide two the first one will be the file name.
The file doesn't exist but we can still go ahead and call Rander.
I'm going to call it projects dot B.S. And then we can specify the options we want to pass to the template.
In this case we're just going to set page title setting and equal to projects with a capital P.
Excellent.
Now with this in place the server file is all done there's no more changes there.
What I am going to do is go ahead and go to the views directory creating a new file called Projects
HB abs in here we'll be able to configure our template to kick things off.
I'm going to copy the template from the About page sense it's really similar.
I'll copy it close about pasted into projects and I'm just going to change this text to project page
text would go here.
Then we can save the file and make our last change and the last thing we want to do is update the header.
We now have a brand new projects page that lives at forward slash projects.
So we're going to want to go ahead and add that to the header links list right here.
I mean to create a new paragraph tag and then I'm going to make a anchor tag.
The text for the link will be projects with a capital P and the graph which is the u r l to visit when
that link is clicked.
We're going to set that equal to forward slash projects just like we do for about where we set it equal
to forward slash about now that we have this in place.
All of our changes are done and we are ready to test things out locally.
I'm going to fire up the app locally using node with server dot jast as the file to start.
We're up on localhost 3000 so over in the browser I can move to the localhost tab as opposed to the
Heroku app tab and click refresh right here.
We have home which goes to home.
We have about which goes to about and we have projects which does indeed go to forward slash projects
rendering the projects page project page text would go here with this in place we're now done locally.
We have the changes.
We've tested them.
Now it's time to go ahead and make that commit.
That's going to happen over inside the terminal.
I'm going to shut down the server and run and get status.
This is going to show me all of the changes to my repository as of the last commit.
I have two modified files.
The server file and the header file and I have my brand new projects file.
All of this looks great.
I want to add all of this to the next commit so I can use a get ad with the DOT to do just that.
Now before I actually make the commit I do like to test that the proper things got added by running
get status right here I can see my changes to be committed are showing up in green.
Everything looks great.
Next up we're going to run and get commit to actually make the commit.
This is going to save all of the changes into the get repository a message for this one would be something
like add project page with a commit made the next thing you needed to do was push up to get up.
This is going to back our code up and let others collaborate on it.
I'm going to use get push to do just that.
Remember we can leave off the origin remote as origin is the default remote.
So if you leave off a remote it'll just use that.
Anyways with our get hub repository updated the last thing to do is deploy to Heroku and we do that
by pushing up the get repository using get push to the Heroku remote.
When we do this we get our long list of logs as the Heroku server goes through the process of installing
our A.P.M. modules building the app and actually deploying it.
Once it's done we're going to get brought back to the terminal like we are here and then we can open
up the you are l in the browser.
Now I can copy it from here or run her Roku open since I already have a tab open with you or Alan place.
I'm going to simply give it a refresh.
Now you might have a little delay as you refresh your app sometimes starting up the app right after
a new app was deployed can take about 10 to 15 seconds.
That's only going to happen as you first visit it other times where you click the refresh button.
It should reload instantly.
Now we have the projects page and if I visit.
Everything looks awesome.
The nav bar is working great and the projects page is indeed rendering at forward slash projects.
With this in place we are now done.
We've gone through the process of adding a new feature.
Testing it locally making a get commit pushing it up to get help and deploying it to Heroku.
We now have a workflow for building a real world web applications using knode.
J.S. this also brings it close to this section in this section you learn about Express and how it can
be used to easily create Web sites.
We can make a web site that returns HGL now or we can make an h t t p u r l that returns some Jason
data.
This is going to let us create all sorts of applications which we'll be doing throughout the rest of
the course.
You also learn about get it get hub Ben Heroku these are the tools.
I prefer to use when I'm creating applications I like to use get because it's super popular.
It's basically the only choice these days.
I like to use GET HOW because it has a great user interface it has a ton of awesome features and pretty
much everyone else is using it too.
There's a great community and I like to use Heroku because it is just dead simple to deploy new versions
of your application.
You can swap out any of these tools with any other tools you can use websites like Amazon Web Services
to host.
You could use bitbucket as your hub alternative.
These are perfectly fine solutions.
All that really matters is you have some tools that are working for you.
You have a repository backed up somewhere whether it's get Hobb or bitbucket and you have an easy way
to deploy.
So you can make changes quickly and get them out to your users fast.
That is it for this section is stay tuned.
I will see you next time