In this video you're going to make your very first note J.S. web server which means you have a whole
new way for users to access your app instead of having them run it from the terminal passing in arguments
you're going to be able to give them a u r l they can visit to view your web app or you are l they can
make an age TTP request to to fetch some data.
This is going to be similar to what we did when we used the G.O. code API instead of using an API though
will be able to create our own.
We'll also be able to set up a static web site for something like a portfolio site.
Both really valid use cases.
Now all of this is going to get done that using a library called Express which is the most popular NPM
library.
It's actually one of the reasons that Noad got so popular because it was so easy to make rest API and
static web servers.
Express is a no nonsense library.
Now there are a lot of different ways to configure it so it can get pretty complex.
That's why we're going to be using it throughout the next couple sections to get started.
Let's make a directory where we can store all of the code for this app.
This app is going to be our web server on the desktop.
I'm going to make a directory called node web server by running M-K Diyar node hyphen web hyphen server.
Once this directory is created I can navigate into it using CD and I can also open it up over inside
of Adam and Adam I'm going to open it up right on the desktop.
Now before we do anything else I want to run NPM in it so we can generate that package.
Jason File right here.
I'm going to run NPM in it.
And I am going to use the default value just by pressing enter through all of the options.
There's no need to customize any of these for the moment.
Then I can type yes.
And there we go.
The package that Jason File is now in place as I mentioned Express is a really big library and they
actually have an entire Web site dedicated to their docs instead of a simple read me empty file.
You can go to express J s dot com to view everything they have to offer.
They are getting started help articles they have guides on how to do things like routing debugging and
error handling and they have an API reference so you can look into exactly what methods you have access
to and what they do.
It's a really handy Web site.
It's important you know it's here.
So down the line you can always refer to it to explore things that we won't get to in this course.
Next up we're going to go ahead and install Express's so we can get started making our web server over
in the terminal.
I'm going to run clear first to clear the output then all run NPM install the module name is express
and we're going to be using the latest version version at four point one four point zero.
I'm also going to provide that a flag to update the dependencies inside of our package.
Jason File once again I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output.
Now that we have the Express installed we can actually create our web server over inside of Adam in
order to run the server we are going to need a file.
I'm going to call this file server.
Yes it's going to sit right in the root of our application.
This is where we'll configure the various routes things like the route of the Web site pages light forward
slash about and so on.
It's also where we'll start the server binding it to a port on our machine.
Now we'll be deploying to a real server later.
We'll talk about how that works for now most of our server examples are going to happen on our local
host inside of a server.
Asked the first thing I want to do is load in express by making a constant call Express and setting
equal to require Express
next up what we're going to do is making new Express app to do this we'll make a variable called app
and we'll set it equal to the return result from calling express as a function.
Now there is no arguments.
We need to pass into Express.
We will be doing a ton of configuration but that's going to happen in a different way.
We'll explore that down below in order to create an app.
All we have to do is call the method down below.
We can start setting up all of our HTP route handlers.
For example if someone visits the root of the Web site we're going to want to send something back maybe
at some Jason data.
Maybe it's an h t m l page.
We can register a handler using app dot get.
This is going to let us set up a handler for an h t t p get request.
There's two arguments we have to pass in to get the first one is going to be the u r l.
In our case we're looking for the root of the app so we can just use forward slash.
And the second argument and this is going to be the function to run the function that tells express
what to send back to the person who made the request.
I'm going to use a simple arrow function.
Excellent.
Now this function is going to get called with two arguments.
These are really important to how Express works.
The first one is request and the second one is response for Questa stores a ton of information about
the request coming in things like the headers that were used.
Any body information the method that was made with the request to the path all of that is stored in
here.
The second argument response has a bunch of methods available to you.
So you can respond to the HTP request in whatever way you like.
You can customize what data you send back.
You could set your age to status codes.
You can do all sorts of things.
I promise we'll be exploring both of these in detail.
For now though what we're going to do is use one method response dot send.
This is going to let us respond to the request sending some data back right in here.
Let's go ahead and call it response.
Send passing in a string in here.
I'm going to type hello express it this is the response for the GTP request.
So when someone views the Web site they're going to see this string if they make a request from an application
they're going to get this back as the body data.
Now at this point we're not quite done.
We have one of our routes set up but the app is never going to actually start listening.
What we need to do is call app dot listen app listen is going to bind the application to a port on our
machine.
In this case for our local host app I'm going to use port three thousand.
A really common port for developing locally.
Later on we'll talk about how to customize this depending on whatever server you use to deploy your
app to production.
For now though a number like three thousand works.
With this in place we are now done.
We have our very first express server and we can actually run things from the terminal and view it in
the browser inside of the terminal.
I'm going to use no demand to start up our app gnomon server.
J.S. and this is going to start up the app and as you're going to see the app never really finishes.
Right now it's hanging it's waiting for requests to start coming in.
The apps that use apt lesson they're never going to stop.
You're going to have to shut them down manually with control C like we've done before.
It might crash if you have an error in your code but it'll never stop.
Normally since we have that binding set up here it's going to listen to requests until you tell it to
stop.
Now that the server is up we can go ahead and move into the browser and open up a new tab.
Visiting the Web site local host colon followed by the port 3000.
This is going to load up the route of the Web site and we specify the handler for that route right here.
Hello Express.
Shows up which is exactly what we expected.
Now there's no thrills there's no formatting.
Nothing too fancy.
We're just sending a string from the server back to the client that made the request.
What I'd like to do from here is open up the developer tools so we can explore exactly what happened
when that request was made inside of chrome.
You can get to the developer tools using settings more tools a developer tools or you can use the keyboard
shortcut shown here for your operating system.
I would highly recommend memorizing that keyboard shortcut because you'll be using the developer tools
a ton in your career with note.
I'm going to open up the developer tools which should look similar to the ones we used when we ran the
note inspector debugger.
They're a little different but the idea is the same.
We have a bunch of tabs up top and then we have our tabs specific information down below.
In our case I want to go to the network tab and currently we have nothing.
So I'm going to go ahead and refresh the page with the tab open and what we see right here is our local
hosts request.
This is the request that's responsible for showing how low express to the screen we can actually go
ahead and click the request to view its details.
This is something we'll be doing extensively throughout the course.
I know this page can be a little overwhelming at first.
There is a heck of a lot of information up top.
We have some general info like the you R-AL that was requested.
The method that the client wanted in this case we made a request and the status code that came back
the default status code being 200.
Meaning that everything went great.
What I'd like to point your attention to is one response header right here under response headers.
We have a header called content type and this header tells the client what type of data came back.
Now this could be something like an H Web site it could be some text it could be send Jason data and
the client could be a web browser or an iPhone or an Android device or any other computer with a network
capabilities.
In our case we're telling the browser that what came back it's some HDMI out.
So why don't you go ahead and render it as such.
We used the text of forward slash HVM l content type.
And this automatically got set by express which is one of the reasons it's so popular it handles a lot
of that mundane stuff for you.
Now that we have a very basic example I want to go ahead and step things up a notch inside of atom we
can actually provide some HVM right inside of send by wrapping our helo express message in an H1 tag.
Now later in this section we're going to be setting up a static web site that has HTL files that get
served up and will also look at templating to create dynamic web pages.
But for now we can actually just pass in some age Yamal to response send.
I'm going to save the server file which should restart things over in the browser.
And when I give it a refresh we get hello expressed printing to the screen.
This time though we have it in an H1 tag which means it's formatted by the default browser styles and
in this case it looks nice and big.
With this in place we can now open up the request inside of the Network tab and what we get is the exact
same thing we had before.
We're still telling the browser that it's HVM now.
Only this time we actually have an H Tamil tag so it gets rendered using the browser's default styles.
The last thing I want to look at before I give you a challenge is how we can send some Jason and data
back sending Jason is really easy with Express to illustrate how he can do it.
I'm going to comment out our current call to response does send an ad a new one.
I'm going to call respond Scott send passing in an object on this object we can provide whatever we
like.
I can go ahead and create a name property setting it equal to the string version of my first name.
I can make a property called likes sending it equal to an array.
And on here I can specify some things I like.
Go ahead and out a few things that you like.
I'm going to add biking as one of them and I'll add cities as another one we call response but send
passing an object express notices that it takes it it converts it into Jason and it sends it back to
the browser.
When I save server dot J ass and gnomon refreshes I can refresh the browser.
And what I get is my data formatted using Jason view which means I can collapse my properties and quickly
navigate that Jasen data.
Now the only reason Jason Vue picked up on this is because that content type header that we explored
in our last request it actually changed.
If I open up localhost a lot of things look the same but now content type has an application forward
SLAs Jason content type this content type tells the requester whether it's an Android phone an I O S
device or the browser that Jason data is coming back and it should parse it as such.
That's exactly what the browser does here.
Express also makes it really easy to set up other routes aside from the route route we can explore that
over inside of atom by calling app get a second time right here.
I'm going to call app dot get I'm going to create a second route.
We'll call this one about then I'm going to provide the handler.
Notice here I just used forward slash about as to route.
It's important to keep that forward slash in place.
But after that you can type whatever you like in this case we're going to have a forward slash about
page that someone can visit.
The handler is going to take the request and the response object.
This is going to let us figure out what kind of request came in and it's going to let us respond to
that request for now.
Just to illustrate we can create more pages will keep the response simple response send inside of the
string I'm going to go ahead and print about page.
Now when I save the server just file the server is going to restart and over in the browser we can visit
forward slash about at forward slash about.
We should now see our new data and that's exactly what we get back about page shows up using apt get
we're able to specify as many routes as we like.
For now we just have an About route and a forward slash route which is referred to as the route route
the right route return some data.
This data happens to be Jason and the about route for turns a little bit of HVM out.
Now that we have this in place and we have a very basic understanding about how we can set up routes
and express I'd like you to go ahead and create a new route as the challenge I'm going to leave a few
comments down below to guide you along the way.
What I'd like you to do is create a route forward slash.
Bad.
This is going to simulate what happens when a request fails.
It's not going to do anything crazy for the moment.
All you're going to do is respond using response don't send.
You're going to send back some Jason data send back Jason with an error message.
Property the error message property can get set to whatever you like.
You can go ahead and use something like unable to fulfill this request or error handling request.
Then I'd like you to go into the browser navigate to forward slash bat and make sure that Jason data
shows up.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you are able to make that new route and visit it in the browser.
Seeing the Jason data you sent back right here.
I'm going to call and get this is going to let us register a nother handler for a get HTP request.
In our case the route we're looking for inside of quotes is going to be forward slash bad.
When someone makes a request for this page what we want to do.
It's going to be specified in the callback the callback is going to take our two arguments request and
response I'm going to use an arrow function which I've used for all of the handlers so far inside of
here the challenge was to send back some Jason.
We're going to do that by calling response Yat-Sen.
But instead of passing in a string or some string HGL we're going to pass in an object now that we have
our object in place we can specify the properties we want to send back.
In this case I told you just to set one error message and to set an error message to whatever you like.
I'm going to go ahead and set my error message property equal to a string unable to handle requests.
Perfect.
Next up I wanted you to save the file restarting it and gnomon and visit it in the browser making sure
your error message showed up correctly in the browser.
I'm going to visit.
Forward slash bad hit enter.
And what do we get.
We get our Jason showing up using Jason view right here.
We have our error message and we have the message showing up on able to handle requests.
Now if you are using Jason view and you want to view the raw Jason data you can actually click view
source and it's going to show you right here in a new tab here we're looking at Dheeraj Jason data where
everything is wrapped in those double quotes.
I'm going to go ahead and stick to the Jason viewed data though because it's a lot easier to navigate
and view you with this in place we are now done the challenge and we're also done the video we now have
a very basic express application up and running it listens on port three thousand and it currently has
handlers for three hours.
When we get the root of the page when we get forward slash about and when we make a get request for
a forward slash bad in the next video we're going to look at how we can set up a static web server.
So when you have an entire directory of javascript images CSSA and HGL you can serve that up easily
without needing to provide routes for everything.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.
I am super excited to keep moving on.