It this video you're going to learn how to set up a static directory.
So if you have a Web site with TMLC access javascript and images you can go ahead and serve that up
without needing to provide a custom route for every single file which would be a real burden.
Now setting this up is really simple.
But before we make any updates to server dot J.S. I want to go ahead and create some static assets inside
of our project that we can actually set up.
In this case we're going to make one.
H.
TMF page that will be able to view in the browser.
Before we get started we do need to create a new directory and everything inside of this directory is
going to be accessible via the web server.
So it's important to not put anything in here that you don't want prying eyes to see everything in here
should be intended to be viewable by anybody.
I'm going to create a public folder to store all of our static assets and inside of here we're going
to go ahead and make an HMO page.
I'm going to create a health page for our example project by creating a file called Help dot HVM.
Now in here we are going to make a quick basic HVM file although I'm not going to touch on all of the
subtleties of HVM Al since this is not really an H Tim L course.
Instead we're going to go ahead and just set up a basic page so take a quick moment to follow along.
The first thing we need to do is create a doc type which lets the browser know what version of each
team malware using that's going to look something like this doc type after the opening tag as well as
the exclamation mark here.
We just type doc type in upper case then we go ahead and provide the actual doc type for h tim L5 the
latest version.
You just type H TNL then we can use the greater then sign to close things up.
Down below we're going to go ahead and open up our HMO tags so we can define our entire H.A. file.
Open and close inside of HVM Alvar's two tags we're going to be using the head to tag which lets us
configure our doc and the body tag which contains everything we want to render to the screen.
I'm going to go ahead and create that hed tag first
inside of head.
We're going to provide two pieces of info.
First up we have to set up the char set which lets the browser know how to render our characters.
Here we're going to go ahead and set Metta and on Metta we're going to set the char set property using
equals and inside of quotes providing the value UTF hyphen 8.
Next up we're going to provide the title tag the title tag lets the browser know what to render in that
title bar where the new tab usually is.
In this case we can set the title to whatever we like.
Help page seems appropriate.
Help page.
Now that our head is configured we can go ahead and add something to the body of our Web site.
This is the stuff that's actually going to be viewable inside of the viewport right here.
I'm going to open and close the body tag and inside of body I'll provide an H-1 title and AP paragraph
tag.
The title is going to match the title we use up above help page perfect and the paragraph will just
have some filler text.
Some text here.
Very cool.
Now we have an h t m l page and the goal is to be able to serve this page up in our express app without
having to manually configure it.
We're going to do that using a piece of express middleware middleware lets you configure how your express
application works.
And it's something we'll be using extensively throughout the course for now.
You can think of it kind of like a third party add on.
You're saying Hey express you usually work like this.
I'd like you to tweak a little bit and work like this in order to add some middleware.
We're going to call app dot use outdoor use it takes the middleware function you want to use.
In our case we're going to be using a built in piece of middleware.
So inside of here we'll be providing the function off of the express object we will be making our own
middleware in this section so don't worry I promise it'll become clear exactly what's getting passed
into use in a little bit.
For now we're going to pass an express dot static and we're going to call it as a function now express
that static takes the absolute path to the folder you want to serve up if we want to be able to serve
up forward slash help.
We're going to need to provide the path to the public folder.
This means we need to specify the path from the root of our hard drive which can be tricky because your
projects move around.
Luckily we have that underscore underscore Durer name and variable.
This is the variable that gets passed into our file by that wrapper function we explored the name it
stores the path to your projects directory.
In this case it stores the path to node web server.
All we have to do is concatenate forward slash public to tell it to use this directory for our server.
I'm going to concatenate using the plus sign the string forwards slash public with this in place we
are now done.
We have our server set up and there's nothing else to do.
Now we should be able to restart our server and access forward slash help.
HGF now and we should see the page we have right here.
Over in the terminal I can now start the app using gnomon server J S.
Once the app is up and running we can visit it in the browser.
I'm going to start by going to localhost three thousand.
Here we get our Jason data which is exactly what we expect.
And if we change that you are able to forward slash help.
H TNL we should get our help page rendering.
And that is exactly what we get.
Right here we have our help page showing to the screen we have the help page title and the some text
here paragraph down below it being able to set up a static directory that easily has made node the go
to choice for simple projects that don't really require a back end.
If you want to create a node app for the sole purpose of serving up a directory you can do it in about
four lines of code.
These three here and the line down below.
Now one more thing I want to talk about is this call to app.
Listen listen does take a second argument.
It's optional.
It's a function.
This will let us do something once the server is up because it can take a little bit of time to get
started.
In our case we're going to cancel that log a message server is up on port three thousand.
Now it's really clear to the person who started the app that the server is actually ready to go because
the message is going to print to the screen.
If I save server J ass and go back into the terminal you can see right here.
Server is up on port 3000 Prince and back inside of the browser we can refresh and we get the exact
same results.
That's it for this one.
We don't have a static directory where we can include javascript CSSA images or any other file types
we like in the next video we're going to continue on learning how to use Express.
We're going to take a look at how we can render dynamic templates kind of like you would with a ph P
or Ruby on Rails file.
You have some variables and you want to render a template injecting those variables.
That's coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.