In the last couple of videos we looked at multiple ways that we can render HTL using Express we pass
them H.T. now into response not send but obviously that was not ideal.
It's a real pain to write your markup in a string.
We also created a public directory where we can have our static HVM all files like our help file and
we can serve these up to the browser.
Both of those work great.
But there is a third solution and that's going to be the topic in this video.
That is a templating engine a template the engine is going to let you render DML but do it in a dynamic
way where you can inject values like a user name or the current date inside of the template.
Kind of like you would in Ruby or HP using this templating engine you're also going to be able to create
reusable markup for things like a header or a footer which is going to be the same on a lot of your
pages.
And this town pulling engine handlebars is going to be the topic of this video and the next.
So let's go ahead and get started.
The first thing we're going to do is install this module.
This is a handlebars iView engine for Express.
Now there are a ton of other view engines for Express for example.
E.J..
Yes or pug.
I'm going with handlebars because I like its syntax the best.
It's a great way to get started.
Now I want to show you a few things inside of the browser.
First up we are going to go to handlebars J s dot com.
This is the documentation for handlebars.
It shows you exactly how to use all of its features.
So if you want to use anything we don't cover inside of course you can always go here to learn how to
use it.
Now the thing we're going to be installing is actually a module that's a wrapper around handlebars.
It's going to let us use it as an express iView engine to view this.
We're going to go to and P.M. J.S. dot com forward slash package forward slash and the package name
is H B S and this is the U R L structure for all packages.
So if you ever want to find a packages page you simply type and Pam Jasc dot com forward slash package
forward slash the package name.
This module is pretty popular.
It's a really great view engine they have a lot of documentation.
I just want to let you know this exists as well.
Now we can go ahead and install it and integrate it into our application over in the terminal.
I'm going to install.
Using NPM install the module name is abs and the most recent version is at four point zero point zero.
And I will be using the saved flag to update package.
Jason No actually configuring express to use this handlebars view engine is super simple.
All we have to do is import and add one statement to our express configuration over inside of atom we're
going to do just that inside of atom.
Let's get started by loading in handlebars Konst.
Yes.
Equals require a B S.
And from here we can go ahead and add that one line right above where I call app use for Express static.
I'm going to call app dot set and this lets us set some various express related configurations.
There's a lot of built in ones we'll be talking about more of them later.
For now though what we're going to do is pass in a key value pair where the key is the thing you want
to set and the value is the value you want to use here.
The key we're setting is.
View engine.
This is going to tell express what view engine we'd like to use and we're going to pass in inside of
quotes.
Could be as perfect and that is all we need to do to get started now in order to create our very first
template.
What I'd like to do is make a directory in the project called views.
Views is the default directory that express uses for your templates.
So what we're going to do is add this and then we'll add a template inside of it.
We've got a directory called views and inside of us we're going to go ahead and make a template for
our About page right here a new file and the file name is going to be whatever you'd like in this case
about Dot.
As this handlebars extension is important.
Make sure to include it.
And Adam already knows how to parse B-S files down below where it shows the current language it's using
it says it's using H.T. M-L in parentheses mustache mustache is used as the name for this type of handle
bars syntax because when you type these curly braces I guess they kind of look like mustaches.
What we're going to do to get started though is take the contents of help h t M-L and copy it directly
I'm going to copy this file so we don't have to rewrite that boilerplate and we'll paste it right in
here.
Now we can go ahead and try to render this page.
I am going to change the H one from help page to about page.
We'll talk about how to dynamically render stuff inside here in just a second.
What I'd like to do at first is just get this rendering over inside of a server.
Yes we already have a route for forward slash about which means we can go ahead and render our template
instead of sending back this about page string.
I'm going to go ahead and remove our call to yes send and we're going to replace it with our Yes Dot
render render is going to let you render any of the templates you have set up with your current view
engine right here.
I do indeed have my about template and I can pass that name about.
HB Yes.
In as the first and only argument we're going to render about Dot h that's perfect.
Now we are done.
This is going to be enough to get that static page rendering.
I'm going to go ahead and save server Dot.
Yes.
And over in the terminal are clear the output.
And I'm going to run our server using gnomon Nordman server.
J.S. once the server is up and running.
Here it is on port three thousand.
We can go ahead and open up this forward slash about u r l and see what we get.
I'm going to head into Krome close some tabs and open up a local host Colan 3000 a forward slash about.
And when I do that what do I get I get my about page rendered just like you'd expected.
We had an H1 tag which shows up nice and big and we have our paragraph tag which shows up below.
So far we have used.
Yes but we haven't actually used any of its features.
Right now we're rendering a dynamic page.
So we might as well have not even included it.
What I want to do is talk about how we can inject data inside of our templates.
Let's come up with some things that we want to make dynamic inside of our handlebars file.
First up we're going to go ahead and make this H-1 tagged dynamic so the page name gets passed into
the template.
And we're also going to add a footer.
For now we'll just make that a simple footer tag
inside of the footer.
We're going to go ahead and out a paragraph and that paragraph is going to have the copyright for our
Web site.
We'll just say something like copyright followed by the year which is 2016 now this year should also
be dynamic.
So as the years change we don't have to manually update our markup.
We're going to go ahead and look at how to make both the 2016 and the about page dynamic which means
they're getting passed in instead of being typed right in the handlebars file in order to do this.
We're going to have to do two things.
We're going to have to pass some data into the template.
This is going to be an object a set of key value pairs and we're going to have to learn how to pull
off some of those key value pairs inside of our handlebars while passing in data is pretty simple.
All you have to do is specify a second argument to Ascot render.
This is going to take an object in on this object.
You can specify whatever you like I might have a page title that gets set equal to about page.
There we go.
We have one piece of data getting injected in the template.
It's not used yet but it is indeed getting injected.
We can also add another one like the current year.
I'm going to put the current year right here and I'm going to set current year equal to the actual year
off of the date javascript constructor.
This is going to look something like this.
We're going to create a new date which makes a new instance of the date object then we're going to use
a method called Get full year which returns the year.
In this case it would return 2016 just like this dot get full year.
Now we have a page title and a current year.
These are both getting passed in and we can go ahead and use them in order to use these pieces of data.
What we have to do inside of our template is use that handle bars syntax which looks a little bit like
this.
You start by opening up to curly braces then you close it to curly braces and you can see that Adam
actually picked up on it automatically and I didn't even need to type the closing brace inside of here.
You can reference any of the props you passed in this case.
I'm going to use page title here Page uppercase t title and down below inside of our copyright paragraph
I'm going to go ahead and use inside of double curly braces current year and with this in place we now
have two pieces of dynamic data and getting injected inside of our application.
No gnomon should have restarted in the background so there's no need to manually do anything there.
And when I refresh the page we do still get about page which is great.
This is coming from the data we defined in server g s and we get copyright 2016 showing up.
This is fantastic.
Well this web page is pretty simple and doesn't look that interesting.
At least you know how to create those servers and inject that data inside of your web page.
All you'd have to do from here is add some custom styles to get things looking nice.
Before we go ahead and get into the challenge I'm going to go ahead and move into the about file and
swap out that title.
Currently it says Help page.
That's leftover from the public folder.
I'm going to change it to some web site awesome.
Now that we have this in place I'm going to go ahead and give you your challenge which is going to be
to create a brand new template and that template is going to get rendered when someone visits the root
of our Web site.
The forward slash route.
Now currently we render some Jason data when I want you to do is replace this with a call to response
Scott render rendering a brand new view home dot H B S.
Now this template doesn't exist you can duplicate the about HBL file or renaming it to home.
H.
B S.
Now inside of home H.B. yes you're going to have the same H-1 you're also going to have your footer
and you're going to have a new property.
Welcome message which needs to get rendered inside of a paragraph tag.
Now the about page is not going to support welcome message but the home page is going to need to.
Which means aside from these two props that get passed and to render you're also going to need to pass
in a third one welcome message and you can set it to whatever you like when you're done.
You should be able to visit that page in a browser.
You should see your page title which should be something like home page.
Your welcome message.
So that equal to whenever you like.
And the copyright showing up.
That's all going to be available at just the root of the Web site localhost 3000.
So take a moment to knock all of that out.
Test it.
And when you're done and you do see things rendering when you visit the root of the Web site you can
go ahead and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully it didn't have too much trouble creating that template and getting it to render.
To get started.
I'm going to duplicate the about JS file so we can start customizing it for our needs.
Duplicate and I'll call this one home.
HB Yes.
Now from here most things are going to stay the same.
We're going to keep the page title in place.
We're also going to keep the copyright and footer down below.
But I do want to change though is this paragraph.
It was fine that the about page had a static one but for the home page we're going to set it equal to
inside of curly braces.
The welcome message property now welcome message is only going to be available on home.
HB Yes which is why I'm specifying it here but not here.
Next up you needed to call.
Response not render inside of the callback.
This is going to let us actually render that page response dot render passing in the template name we
want to render this one is called home.
Yes.
Then we're going to pass in our data now to get started.
We can go ahead and pass the page title.
I'm going to set this equal to home page and we'll pass in some sort of generic welcome message Welcome
to my Web site.
Really great user experience there.
And then we're going to pass in the current year and we already know how to fetch the current year new
date and on the Date object we're going to call that get full year method and get full year perfect
with this in place.
All you needed to do was save the file which is automatically going to restart the server using gnomon
and refresh the browser.
When I do that what do I get.
I get my home page title my welcome to my Web site message and my copyright with the year 2016 right
here.
And if I go to forward slash about everything still looks great.
We have our dynamic page title and copyright and we have our static some text here text with this in
place we are now done with the very basics of handlebars.
Hopefully you see how this can be useful inside of a real world web app.
Aside from a realistic example like the copyright other reasons you might use this is to inject some
sort of dynamic user data things like a username and email or anything else now that you have a basic
understanding about how to use handlebars to create static pages.
We're going to go ahead and look at some more advanced features of abs.
Inside of the next video I'm super excited to get to it because it's going to be really fantastic stuff.
So stay tuned.
I'll see you soon