In this video you're going to learn a few more advanced features that handlebars has to offer.
This is going to make it easier to render your markup especially markup that's used in multiple places
and it's going to make it easier to inject dynamic data into your web pages in order to illustrate the
first thing we're going to talk about.
I want to open up both about HECS and home.
HB Yes.
And you'll notice that down at the bottom they both have the exact same photo code.
We have a little copyright message for both and they both have the same header area which is the H-1
tag in the future.
They might have links that links to other pages a logo or anything like that.
But for now it's just in each one.
Now this really isn't a problem because we have two pages but as you add more and more pages it's going
to become a real pain to update your hatter and your footer.
You're gonna have to go into every file and manage the code there.
But we're going to talk about instead is something called a partial.
A partial is a partial piece of your web site.
It's something you can reuse throughout your templates.
For example we might have a foot or partial that renders the footer code.
You can include that partial on any page you need a footer.
You can do the same thing for Hetter in order to get started the first thing we need to do is set up
our server.
Jeff's file just a little bit to let handlebars know that we want to add support for partials in order
to do this.
We're going to add one line of code right here above where we declare our view engine and it's going
to look something like this.
HB Yes Dot register Parshall's no register Parshall's with a capital P in Parshall's that is going to
take the directory you want to use for all of your handlebar partial files and we're going to be specifying
that directory as the first and only argument.
Once again this does need to be the absolute directories.
I'm going to use the underscore underscore Durr name variable right here.
Then we can concatenate the rest of the path which is going to be a forward slash.
News.
And in this case I want you to use forward slash Parshall's.
We're going to store our partial files right inside of a directory in the views folder.
Now we can go ahead and create that folder right in views called Parshall's inside of here.
We can put any of the handlebars Parshall's we like to illustrate how they work.
We're going to go ahead and create one called footer dot h B-S FOTR dot B-S and inside of here we have
access to the same handlebars features which means we can write some markup.
We can inject variables we can do whatever we like.
For now we're going to do is copy the footer tag exactly pasting it inside a footer.
Yes.
Now we have our foot in on HB as file.
This is the partial and we can include in both about and home.
Let's go ahead and do that in order to do that we're going to delete the code that we already have in
the partial and we're going to replace it with opening and closing two curly braces.
Now instead of injecting data we want to inject a template and the syntax for that is to add a greater
than symbol with the space followed by the partial name.
In our case that partial is called the footer.
So we can add this right here and then I can go ahead and save about and do the same thing over and
home.
H Yes.
Over at home.
Abs.
I'm going to delete the footer and replace it with the syntax to inject the footer partial.
And there we go.
We now have a footer partial It's rendering on both pages.
To illustrate how this works I'm going to fire up my server and by default gnomon it's not going to
watch your handlebars files.
So if you make a change the Web site's not going to render as you might expect.
We can fix this by running gnomon passing in server dot J S and providing the e flag.
This lets us specify all of the extensions we want to watch.
In our case we're going to watch the s extension for the server file and after the comma the H B.
Extension.
Perfect.
Now our app is up and running.
We can go ahead and refresh things over in the browser and this should look the same.
We have our About page with our footer and we have our home page with the exact same footer.
The advantage now is if we want to change that footer we just do it in one place over and footer.
HB Yes I can add something to our footer paragraph tag.
I'm going to add a little message created by Andrew Mead with a hyphen.
Save the file and now when I refresh the browser right here we have a brand new footer.
It's going to show up for both the home page and the About page.
There's no need to do anything manual in either of these pages.
And this is the real power of Parshall's.
You have some code you want to reuse it inside of your web site.
So you simply create a partial and you inject it wherever you like.
And now that we have the footer partial in place it's going to be your challenge to create the header
partial.
That means you're going to need to create a brand new file header.
HB Yes you're going to want to add the each one tag inside of that file and then you're going to render
the partial in bult about abs and home.
HB Yes both pages should still look the same.
Now in order to test that it actually worked.
Go ahead and add a special character right after the H-1 like Jay or one to three just to make sure
that what you typed in the partial is actually what's rendering and it's not left over from the pages
we have here.
We'll go ahead and clean that up after the challenge.
So take a moment create that brand new header file add it inside of both about and home test it.
And when you're done go ahead and click play
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to create that and you were able to render it inside of our website pages.
I'm going to get started by creating a new file in the Parshall's folder called hetter dot H.B. s inside
of Hedegaard abs.
We're going to take the H one tag from our website paste it right inside and save it.
Now we can go ahead and use this hetter partial in both files inside of about you needed to do this
using the syntax.
The double curly braces with the greater than sign followed by the partial name header and we're going
to do the exact same thing for the home page in the home page.
I'll delete our H-1 tag inject the header and save the file.
Now I do want to create something slightly different just so I can test that it actually is using the
partial I'm going to type 1 2 3 right after the H-1 tag.
Now that all my files are saved I should be able to refresh the browser and right here I see about Page
1 2 3 printing which is fantastic.
This means the header partial is indeed working.
And if I go back to the home page everything still looks great.
Now that we have the header broken out into its own file we can do all sorts of things.
We can take our H-1 tag and put it inside of a header tag which is the appropriate way to declare your
header inside of HVM out.
Right here we add an opening and closing header tag.
We can take the H-1 and we can move it right inside.
We can also go ahead and add some links to the other pages on our website.
Now this isn't going to look nice because I'm not going to go into any styling at the moment but we
could add an anchor tag right here for the home page by adding a tag
inside of the a tag will specify the link text.
We'd like to show up.
I'm going to go with home.
Then inside of the H ref attribute we can specify the path the link should take you to.
Which would just be forward slash.
Then we can take the same paragraph tag copy it and paste it down below and make a link for the about
page.
I'll change the page text to about excuse me the link text and then you are out instead of going to
forward slash is going to go to forward slash.
About now we've made a change to our header file and it's going to be available on all of the pages
of our Web site.
I'm on the home page if I refresh when I get home and about I can click about to go to the About page
and then I can click home to come right back.
All of this is much easier to manage now that we have Parshall's inside of our Web site.
Now before we go there is one more thing I want to talk about.
This is a handlebars helper handlebars.
Helpers are going to be ways for you to register functions to run to dynamically create some output.
For example inside of a server.
Yes we currently inject the current year inside of both of our templates and that's not really necessary.
There is a better way to pass this data in this data shouldn't need to be provided because we're always
going to be using the exact same function.
We're always going to take the new date get full year return value passing it in.
Instead we're going to use a partial and all set up right now.
Now a partial is nothing more than a function you can run from inside of your handlebars templates.
Oh we need to do is register it and I'm going to do that up above right below where we set up our express
middleware right here.
We're going to call each B-S dot register and we're going to be registering a helper.
So we're going to call register helper now register helper takes two arguments it takes the name of
the helper as the first argument and the function to run as the second the first argument right here
is going to be get current year in our case we're going to create a helper that returns that current
year.
The second argument is going to be our function.
I'm going to use an arrow function and anything we return from this function is going to get rendered
in place of the get current year call.
That means if I call get current year inside of the footer it's going to return the year from the function
and that data is what's going to get rendered over in server dot J.
Yes we can return the year by using a return and having the exact same code we have down below.
We'll make a new date and we're going to call it get full year method.
Now that we have a helper we can remove this data from every single one of our run during calls which
is going to be really fantastic because there really is no need to compute it for every page since it's
always the same.
Now that we've removed that data from the individual calls to render we are going to have to use get
current year inside of the footer instead of referencing current and year we are going to use the helper
get current year and there's no need for any special syntax.
When you use something inside of curly braces that clearly isn't a partial handlebars is first going
to look for a helper with that name.
If there is no helper it will look for a piece of data with that get current year name.
In this case it is going to find the helper.
So everything is going to work as expected.
We can now go ahead and save FOTR dot abs move into the browser and give things or refresh.
When I refresh the page we still get copyright 20:16 right here.
And if I go to the About page everything looks great and we can prove that that data is coming back
from our helper by simply returning something else.
I'm going to go ahead and comment on that code.
And before the comment I'm going to return test just like this.
I can now save server us refresh the browser and we get task showing up right here.
So the data that renders right after the copyright word is indeed coming from that helper.
Now I'm going to go ahead and remove the code so we return the proper year.
Now our helpers.
They could also take arguments.
And this is really useful stuff.
Let's go ahead and create a second helper that's going to be a capitalization helper we'll call the
helper's screen it and its job is going to be to take some text and it's going to return that text in
upper case in order to do this.
We will be calling h B-S dot register helper again this helper as I mentioned will be called screen
at.
And it is going to take a function because we do need to run some code in order to do anything useful.
Now scream it is going to take the text to scream and oh it's going to do is call on that string the
two upper case method I'm going to return text dot to upper case just like this.
Now we can actually go ahead and use scream in one of our files.
I'm going to move into home.
H B-S right here we have our welcome message.
I'm going to remove it and we're going to scream the welcome message in order to pass that data into
one of our helpers.
We first have to reference the helper by name.
Scream it.
And then after a space we can specify whatever data we want to pass in as arguments.
In this case we're going to pass in the welcome message but we could also pass into arguments by typing
a space and passing in some other variable which we don't have access to.
For now we're going to go ahead and use it like this which means we're calling these scream at Halpert
passing in one argument.
Welcome message.
Now I can go ahead and save home.
HB.
Moved back into the browser go to the home page and right here.
Welcome to my Web site.
In all upper case and this is fantastic.
Using handlebars helpers we can create both functions that don't take arguments and functions that do
take arguments so you need to do something to the data inside of your web page.
You can do that with javascript.
Now that we have this in place we are done.
We've learned a little bit about handlebars Parshall's which let us create reusable chunks of code like
headers and footers and we also learn about handle bars helpers which is a way to run some javascript
code from inside of your handle bars.
Templates both are really useful.
Super great features when you're using handlebars.
That is it for our little two part series on handlebars in the next video we're going to move back to
talking about Express and how it can customize our requests our responses and our server.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.