In this video you're going to learn how to use Express middleware express middleware is a fantastic
tool.
It allows you to add on to the existing functionality that Express has.
So if Express doesn't do something you'd like it to do.
You can add some middleware and teach it how to do that thing.
Now we've already used a little bit of middleware right here on line 8.
We use a middleware and we teach express how to read from a static directory we call apt use which is
how you register middleware then and we provided the middleware function we want to use now middleware
can do anything.
You could just execute some code like logging something to the screen.
You could make a change to the request or the response object will be doing just that in later sections.
When we add API authentication we'll want to make sure the right header is sent that letter is going
to be expected to have an API token.
We can use middleware to determine whether or not someone's logged in.
Basically whether or not they should be able to access a specific route and we can also use middleware
to respond to a request we could send something back from the middle where just like we would anywhere
else using response to render or response send.
Now in order to explore middleware we're going to create some basic middleware right now just below
where we call apt use registering our express static middleware.
We're going to call app use again now.
Apt use is how you register middleware and it takes a function right here.
We're going to pass in an Aero function the use function.
It takes just one function there is no need to add any other arguments.
This function is going to get called with the request object and the response object and a third argument
next.
Now request Cressingham response.
Those should seem familiar by now.
It's the exact same arguments we get whenever we register a handler down below.
Next is where things get a little trickier.
Next exists so you can tell express that when your middleware function is done and this is useful because
you can have as much a middleware as you like register to a single express app.
For example I have some middleware that serves up a directory.
We're going to write some more that logs some request data to the screen and we could have a third piece
down below that helps with application performance keeping track of response times.
All of that is possible now inside of this function we can do anything we like we might like something
to the screen we might make a database request to make sure a user is authenticated.
All of that is perfectly valid and we use next to tell express when we're done.
So if we do something asynchronous the middleware is not going to move on only when we call next like
this.
Will the application continue to run.
Now this means if your middleware doesn't come next your handlers for each request they're never going
to fire.
We can prove this right here.
I'm going to call apt use passing in an empty function.
I'm going to save the file and over in the terminal I'm going to run our app using gnomon with server.
Yes I'm going to do this.
I'm going to move into the browser and I'll make a request for the home page.
I'm going to refresh the page and you can see that up top it is trying to load but it's never going
to finish.
No it's not that it can't connect to the server it's connecting to the server just fine.
The real problem is that inside of our app we have middleware that doesn't call next to fix this.
All we're going to do is call next like this.
Now when things refresh over inside of the browser we get our home page exactly as we expected.
The only difference is now we have a place where we can add on some functionality right inside of here.
We're going to get started by creating a logger that's going to log out all of the requests that come
into the server.
We're also going to story time stamp so we can see exactly when someone made a request for a specific
you are able to get started inside of the middleware.
Let's go ahead and get the current time.
I'm going to make a variable called now.
Setting it equal to new date creating a new instance of our Date object.
And I'm going to call its two string method two string creates a nice formatted date a human readable
time stamp.
Now that we have are now variable in place we can go ahead and start creating the actual logger by calling
console lock.
I can call console log passing in whatever I like.
I'm going to pass in inside of Tick's the now a variable with a call and after we'll tack on some more
data in just a moment.
Now if I saved my file things are going to restart over in the terminal because nobody is running.
And when I make a request for the site again and I go into the terminal I should see my log and right
here I have my log.
Currently it's just a time stamp but we are on the right track now.
Everything is working because we called next.
So after this consulate that log call prints to the screen our application continues and it serves up
the page inside of here we can add on more functionality by exploring that request object on the request
object.
We have access to everything about the request.
The HTP method the path query parameters anything that comes from the client whether that clients an
app a browser or an iPhone.
It is all going to be available in that request object.
Two things we're going to pull off now is the HTP method and the path if you want to look at a full
list of the things you have access to.
You can go to express J.S. dot com go to API reference.
We happen to be using a four point X version of Express's I'm going to click that link then on the right
we have both request and response.
We're looking for the request object so a click that we're going to be using to request you R-AL and
request dot method back inside of Adam.
We can start implementing those.
Adding them into console that lock right after the time stamp we're going to print the HTP method.
We'll be using other methods later.
For now we've only used the get method right inside of here.
I'm going to inject the request dot method printing it to the console.
Next up we can go ahead and print the path so we know exactly what page the person requested.
I'm going to do that by injecting another variable request.
You are out with this in place we don't have a pretty useful piece of middleware.
It takes the request object it spits out some information and then it moves on letting the server process
the request down below.
If I saved the file and I rerun the app from the browser I should be able to move into the terminal
and see this new logger printing to the screen and right here we get just that we have our time stamp
we have the HTP method which is get and we have the path.
If we change the path to something more complicated like forward slash about and I move back into the
terminal we're going to see that forward slash about right here where we accessed request dot you are
out.
Now this is a pretty basic example of some middleware we can take it a step further.
Aside from just logging a message to the screen we're also going to print that message to a file.
Let's go ahead and load in f s up above.
I'm going to create a constant call that constant f s and set that equal to the return result from requiring
the module awesome.
Now we can go ahead and implement that down below.
I'm going to take our template string which is currently defined inside of console log.
I'm going to cut it out and instead store in a variable I'm going to make a variable called log setting
and equal to that template string.
Now we can pass that log variable into both console log and into an F as method to write to our file
system.
I'm going to call FS append file now as you remember append file lets you add onto a file.
It takes two arguments.
The file name and the thing you want to add the file name we're going to use is server dot Lague will
create a nice log file and the actual contents is just going to be the log message up above.
And we are going to need to add one more thing.
We also want to move on to the next line after every single request gets logged.
So I'm going to concatenate the new line character which is going to be backslash and perfect.
Hello this is Andrew a few months after the Noad course was originally released.
If you're using Knode these 7 or greater you're going to need to make a small tweak to this line as
you can see here we added a third argument to FS a pen file.
This is a callback function.
It's now required if you don't have a callback function.
You're going to get a deprecation warning over inside of the console.
Now as you can see our callback function here takes an error argument if there is an error we just print
a message to the screen that's it.
If you change your line to look like this regardless of your node version you'll be future proof.
If you're on Node 7 or greater the warning in the console will go away.
Now the warning is going to say something like deprecation warning calling an asynchronous function
without callback is deprecated.
If you see that warning make this change.
All right let's get back to it.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and test things out.
I saved the file which should be restarting things over inside of gnomon Nordman is restarted right
now and inside of Krome I can go ahead and give the page a refresh if I head back into the terminal.
I do still get my log which is great.
Notice I also have a request for a FOV icon.
Eico.
This is usually the icon that shown in the browser tab.
I have one cached from a previous project.
There actually is no icon file defined which is totally fine.
The browser still makes the request anyways which is why that shows up here inside of Adam.
We don't have our server log file and if I open it up right here we have a log of all the requests that
were made.
We have time stamps we have HTP methods and we have pads and this is pretty awesome.
Using app use we were able to create some middleware that helps us keep track of how our server is working.
Now there are times where you might not want to call.
Next we learned that we could call next after we do something asynchronous like a read from a database.
But imagine something goes wrong.
You can avoid calling next to never move on to the next piece of middleware and that's exactly what
you're going to do.
The challenge for this video.
What I would like you to do is create a new view inside the views folder.
Go ahead and call this one maintenance.
H B S.
This is going to be a handle bars.
Template will render when the site is in maintenance mode.
You can give it a really simple structure.
Copy it from home or about just some basic HTL Yamal there is no reason to use the Parshall's.
All I want you to do is render an H1 tag something like.
We'll be right back and a paragraph tag something like the site is currently being updated.
We'll be back soon.
Now once you make that maintenance H.B. as a template file I want you to render it inside of a new piece
of middleware.
We don't have that middleware defined yet.
You're going to have to call apt use again to defining the function but inside of there you'll be able
to call a response rendered just like you did down below.
There's no difference between the response object you get here in a request handler and their response
object you get in Middleware.
They are exactly the same object.
That means you only need to add one line inside of the middle where you just have to call response not
render.
No need to call next since we don't actually want to move on to the rest of the request.
We simply want to stop it rendering the maintenance abs file to the screen so take a moment to knock
all that out.
It's going to require you to call apt use define the function and add one call inside of the function.
Once you're done go ahead and test it out try to make a request to a page and see what happens when
you do that.
You should get your template from maintenance.
Yes printing instead.
Take a moment pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play.
All right I know that one might have been a little tricky.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble getting that set up.
The first thing I'm going to do is make the maintenance.
HBL file by duplicating home Don H.B. us.
I'm going to call the file maintenance.
Yes and inside of maintenance.
HB Yes.
All I'm going to do is wipe the body and add a few tags right here.
I'll add an H1 tag to print a little message to the user.
I'm going to go ahead and use something like.
We'll be right back down below.
I can go ahead and add a paragraph tag notice there.
I was able to use P followed by the tab.
This is a shortcut inside of Adam for creating an HMO tag that works for all tags.
I could type body and hit enter or I could type P and hit enter inside the paragraph I'm going to leave
a little message.
The site is currently being updated perfect now that we have our template file in place we can go ahead
and define our maintenance middleware which is going to bypass all of our other handlers where we render
other files and print Jason and instead it'll just render this template to the screen.
I'm going to save the file move into server.
Yes.
And define that middleware right here.
I can call app use passing in our function.
The function is going to take those three arguments request response and next down below.
All we're going to need to do is call response dot render response dot render passing in the name of
the file.
We want to render in this case it's maintenance.
HB Yes.
Then there we go.
That is all you needed to do to set up our maintenance middleware.
This middleware is going to stop everything after it from executing.
We don't call next.
So the actual handlers right here they are never going to get executed.
We can prove this over inside of the browser.
I'm going to go ahead and refresh the page.
And what do I get.
I get the maintenance page.
I can go to the home page and I get the exact same thing.
If you see this then you completed the challenge successfully.
Now there's one more really really important piece to middleware I haven't yet talked about and you
might have seen it if you tested out your maintenance middleware.
Remember inside of that public folder right there we have a help.
H TNL file.
If I visit that in the browser by going to forward slash help h DML I'm going to still get that help
page I'm not getting the maintenance page.
That is because middleware is executed in the order you call app use which means the first thing we
do is we set up our express static directory then we set up our logger.
And finally we set up our maintenance B-S logger.
This is a pretty big problem.
If we also want to make the public directory files like help that shemale private We're going to have
to reorder our calls to app use because currently the Express server is responding inside of the Express
static middleware.
So our maintenance middleware doesn't get a chance to execute.
I'm going to take the app use Express static call remove it from the file and add it down below after
we render the maintenance file to the screen.
Now everything is going to work as expected no matter what we're going to log the request which is great.
Then we'll check if we're in maintenance mode if this thing is here if it is will render the maintenance
file if it's not we'll ignore it because it will be commented out or something like that.
And finally we'll be using Express static that this is going to fix all those problems.
If I rerun the app now I get the maintenance page on help.
And now if I go back to the root of the web site I still get the maintenance page which is great.
Now once I'm done with my maintenance middleware I can always go ahead and comment it out.
This is going to remove it from being executed and the Web site will work as expected.
We'll log some stuff will render our static files and we'll also be rendering our other routes down
below with it commented out.
I can now refresh and get my home page back which is awesome.
This has been a quick dive into Express and middleware.
We're going to be using it a lot more throughout the course where we're using middleware to check if
our API requests are actually authenticated inside of them middleware we'll be making a database request
checking if the user is indeed who they say they are.
That's coming up later though for now in the rest of this section we're going to worry about adding
version control and deploying our applications because when it comes to creating real world node apps
deploying your app to the web is obviously a pretty big part of that.
It's all coming up next starting with get.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.