In this video you're going to learn how to set up and use get which is a version control system get
it going to let you keep track of the changes to your project over time.
This is really useful when something goes wrong and you need to revert to a previous state in the project
where things were working.
It's also super useful for backing up your work.
Now in the real world every single company uses some form of version control is essential to the software
development process and most of them are using GET GET has become really popular dominating the market
share for version control yet is also free and open source.
And there is a ton of great educational material.
They have a book on how to learn get it's free and Stack Overflow is filled with get specific questions
and answers in this course.
We're going to be using get to save our project.
We're also going to be using it to back up our work to a service called Get hub.
And finally we'll be using get to deploy our project live to the Web.
So we'll be able to take our web server and deploy it for anybody to visit.
It won't just be available on local host to get started you are going to need to install get on your
computer but luckily for you it is a really simple installation process.
There is nothing crazy you need to do.
It's one of those installers where you just click next through a few steps.
Let's go ahead and do that.
We can grab the installer by heading over to the browser and going to get hyphen SOCOM dot com here
we can find a lot of resources about how to use it as well as download the installer.
Before we go ahead and install it I want to show you this link down here to the book called Pro get
it as a free book and you can read it online.
It covers everything that it has to offer.
We'll be looking at some of the more basic features in this course but I could easily create an entire
course on get there actually is you to me courses just on get and get hub.
So if you want to learn more than what we cover here I'd recommend reading this book or checking out
a course whatever your preferred learning method is on the right hand side of the home page you're going
to have a little computer screen that should have a download button for your operating system whether
it's Windows Linux or Mac.
You can go ahead and click that which should take you to the installer page.
Now lately there's been a problem with sourceforge where you have to actually click here to download
manually in order to start the download.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And after five seconds we should be able to get the installer downloading.
Once it's done we can simply run it.
Here we go.
The installer is downloading I'm going to go back to get and get off of Source Forge since it's got
a ton of ads super annoying down below we have the installer.
I'm going to go ahead and click it.
You should be seeing a screen similar to mine whether you're on Linux OS X or Windows.
Now the installer might start for you if you're on OS X you're going to need to launch the package installer
and you might get this message saying that it's from an unidentified developer.
This is because it is distributed via a third party as opposed to being in the OS X app store.
We can go ahead and right click click open and confirm that we do indeed want to open it.
Once you're out the installer the process is going to be pretty simple you can essentially Click Continue
and next throughout every step if you're on Windows though there is an important distinction inside
of the installer you're going to see a screen just like this.
It is really important that you also install get a bash as shown here you get.
BASH is a program that simulates a Linux type terminal and it's going to be really essential when we
create our S-sh keys and the next video to uniquely identify our machine.
For now though we can go ahead and move through the installer if you're on Windows.
Make sure you install and get back as well.
Continue install.
I'm going to confirm by typing my password then the installer should get moving.
Once it's done we can go ahead and actually test that thing's installed successfully.
I'm going to close it down.
I'm also going to close down the directory and move in to the terminal from the terminal.
We can go ahead and run it get hyphen hyphen version this is going to print the version of Get you have
installed and right here you can see I have get version 2 point nine point two.
Now if you have your terminal still open and you're getting an error like get command not found I'd
recommend trying to restart your terminal.
Sometimes that is required when you're installing new commands like the get command which we just installed
from here though we are ready to turn our node web server directory into a get repository in order to
do this.
We're going to run a command called Get in it and get in it needs to get executed from the root of your
project.
The folder that has everything that you want to keep track of.
In our case the node web server is that folder it has our server japes file are packaged up Jason File
and all of our directories right here from the server folder.
I'm going to run get in it and all this does is it creates a dot get directory inside of that folder
and I can prove that by running.
LS hyphen a.
Go ahead and run these commands.
From a get bash.
If you're on Windows right here I get all of the directories including the hidden ones and right here
I do indeed have dot get.
Now this directory is not something you should be manually updating.
We're going to be using commands from the terminal in order to make changes to the get folder.
You don't want to be going in there manually messing around with things because there's a pretty good
chance you're going to corrupt the repository and all of your hard work is going to become useless.
Now obviously if it's backed up it's not a big deal.
But there really is no reason to go into that get folder.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output.
And now we can start looking at exactly how it works.
As I mentioned how good is responsible for keeping track of the changes to your project but by default
it doesn't actually track any of your files.
We have to tell get exactly which files we want it to keep track of.
And there's a good reason for this.
There are files in every project that you're most likely not going to want to add to your get repo and
we'll talk about which ones and why in just a second.
For now let's go ahead and run a command.
Get status.
Now all these commands and need to get executed from inside of the root of the project.
If you try to run this outside of a repository you're going to get an error like get repository not
found.
What that means is that it cannot find that data get directory in order to actually get the status of
your repository.
When we run this command we're going to get some output that looks like this.
And the important piece is for now is the untracked files hatter and all of the files underneath it.
These are all of the files and folders that get seized.
But it is currently not tracking get doesn't know if you want to keep track of the changes to these
files or if you want to ignore them from your repository.
Now the views fall there for example this is something we definitely want to keep track of.
This is going to be essential to the project and we want to make sure that when ever someone downloads
the repository they get the views folder the logfile on the other hand it doesn't really need to be
included in get.
In general our log files are not going to be committed since they usually contain information specific
to a point in time when the server was running.
Right here we have server.
Yes our public folder and package.
Jason.
These are all essential to the process of executing the app.
These are definitely going to be added to our Get repository and up above.
We have the node modules folder the node modules folder is what's called the generated folder generated
folders are easily generated by running a command.
In our case we can regenerate this entire directory using NPM install.
We're not going to want to add node modules to our Get repository because its contents differ depending
on the version of NPM you have installed and depending on the operating system you're using it's best
to leave off node modules and let every person who uses your repository manually install the modules
on the machine when they're actually going to be running the app.
Now we have these six folders and files listed right here.
So let's go ahead and add the four we want to keep to get started.
We're going to use it to get ad command and get ad lets you tell Get you want to keep track of a certain
file.
I'm going to type and get ad space package dot Jason after I do this I can run it get status again and
this time we get something very different.
Now we have an initial commit Hatter this is new and we have our old untracked files Hatter notice under
ontrack files.
We don't have package dot Jason anymore that has moved up to the initial commit hetter.
These are all of the files that are going to be saved.
Also known as committed when we make our first commit which we'll do in just a little bit.
Now we can move on adding the three others I'm going to use to get add again to tell get we want to
track that public directory.
I can run get status to confirm it was added as expected.
Right here you can see the public help file is now going to be committed to get.
Once we run a commit.
Next up we can add server dot J S with a get AD server dot J.S. and we can add the used directory using
a get add views just like this.
I'm going to run and get status to confirm.
Everything looks good and it does indeed look good.
Now these ontrack files they're going to sit around here until we do one of two things.
We either add them to the get repository or we ignore them using a custom file that we're going to create
over inside an atom inside of atom.
Well I'd like to do in the route of your project is make a new file called Dot get.
Ignore the good ignore file is going to be part of our Get repository and that tells which folders and
files you want to ignore.
In this case we can go ahead and ignore Noad underscore modules just like this.
When we save the get ignore file and rerun get status from the terminal we're now going to get a really
different result down below.
You can see we have a new on Tracht file get ignore but the node modules directory is nowhere in sight
and that's exactly what we want we want to remove this completely.
Making sure that it never ever ever gets added to the get Ribault.
Next up we can go ahead and ignore that server data logfile by typing its name server log.
Right here I'm going to go ahead and save ignore.
Run and get status from the terminal.
One more time and make sure everything looks great right here.
We have.
Get ignore as our only untracked file it is server logfile and node modules are nowhere in sight.
Now that we have get ignore we are going to be adding it to get using get ad datt get ignore.
Excellent.
Now when I run get status we should be able to see that all of the files that show up are under the
initial commit.
So now it's time to make a commit no commit really only requires two things.
It requires some change in the repository.
In this case we're teaching get how to track a ton of new files so we are indeed changing something
and it requires a message.
Now we've already handled the file part of things we've told get what we want to save.
We just haven't actually saved it yet.
In order to make our first commit and save our first thing into the get repository we're going to run
get commit and we are going to be providing one flag.
The flag which is short for message after their inside of quotes we can go ahead and specify the message
that we want to use for this commit.
It's really important to use these messages so when someone is digging through the commit history the
list of all the changes to the project are actually useful.
In this case initial commit is always a good message for your first commit.
I'm going to go ahead and hit enter and write here.
You see all of the changes that happened to the repo we have created a bunch of new files inside of
the repository.
These are all of the files that we told get we want to keep track of and this is fantastic.
We now have our very first commit which essentially means that we've saved the project at its current
state.
If we make a big change to server dot G-S messing stuff up and we can't figure out how to get it back
to the way it was we can always get it back because we made a get commit now we're going to explore
some more fancy get things in the future.
We'll be talking about how to do most of the things you want to do with get including deploying to Heroku
and pushing to get hub.
But for now that is it we're just looking at how to add files to get and how to make that first commit.
We'll talk more about get soon in the next video.
We're going to be setting up both get help and Heroku then we'll worry about how to push our code and
deploy it.
I am super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you soon.