It now that you have a local get repository we're going to look at how we can take that code and push
it up to a third party service called Get hub get how that is going to let us host our repositories
remotely.
So if our machine never crashes we can get our code back.
And it also has great collaboration tools so we can open source a project letting others use our code
or we can keep it private.
So only people we choose to collaborate with can see the source code.
Now in order to actually communicate between our machine and get how we're going to have to create something
called an S-sh key S-sh keys were designed to securely communicate between two computers.
In this case it's going to be our machine and the get hub server.
This is going to let us confirm that get hub is who they say they are and it's going to like get help
confirm that we indeed have access to the code we're trying to alter.
This is all going to be done with S-sh keys and we're going to create them first then we'll configure
them and finally we'll push our code up to get up the process of setting up S-sh keys can be a real
burden.
This is one of those videos I have in most of my courses and it often gets the most questions because
there's really small room for error if you type any of the commands wrong things are just not going
to work as expected.
So if you pay attention closely to any video let it be this one.
Now if you're on Windows you're going to need to do everything I do in this video from a get bash as
opposed to the regular command prompt because we're going to be using some commands that just are not
available on Windows.
They are however available on Linux and Mac.
So if you're using either of those operating systems you can continue using the terminal you've been
using throughout the course.
Before we dive into the commands I want to show you a quick guide that exists online in case you get
stuck or you have any questions you can google get hub S-sh key is and this is going to link you to
an article called that generating an S-sh key and once you're here you'll be able to click this S-sh
breadcrumb.
And this is going to bring you back to all of their articles on S-sh keys.
These four right here the nested four are the ones we're going to be focusing on checking if we have
a key generating a new key adding the key to get.
And finally testing that everything worked as expected.
If you run into any problems along any of these steps you can always click the guide for that step and
you can pick the operating system you're using.
So you can see the appropriate commands for that OS.
Now that you know this exists let's go ahead and do it together.
The first command we're going to run from the terminal is going to check if we have an existing S-sh
key.
Now if you don't that's fine.
We're going to go ahead and create one.
If you do or you're not sure you do you can run the following command to confirm whether or not you
have one ls with the a al flag.
This is going to print all of the files in a given directory and the directory were S-sh keys are stored
by default on your machine is going to be at the user directory which you can use.
Tell us a shortcut for forward slash dot S-sh.
When you run the command you're going to see all of the contents inside of that S-sh directory.
In this case I've deleted all of my S-sh keys so I have nothing inside in my directory.
I just have a path for the current directory and the previous one.
Now that we have this in place and we've confirmed we don't have a key we can go ahead and generate
one.
If you do already have a key a file like ID underscore RSA You can go ahead and skip the process of
generating the key to make a key.
We're going to use the S-sh hyphen key Jeon command.
Now the S-sh hyphen key.
Jan with an end the command takes three arguments we're going to pass in the setting equal to RSA.
We're going to pass in B which is for bytes.
Setting that equal to 42 96.
Make sure to match these arguments exactly.
And we're going to be setting a capital C flag which is going to get set equal to your e-mail.
Now the scope of what's actually happening behind the scenes is not part of this course.
S-sh keys and setting up security that could be an entire course in and of itself.
We're going to be using this command to simplify the entire process right here.
I'm going to type in my email.
Andrew Joseph Meade at gmail dot com.
Perfect.
Now I can go ahead and hit enter which is going to generate two new files in our S-sh folder.
When you run this command you're going to get greeted with a few steps.
I want you to use the default for all of them.
Here they want to ask you if you want to customize the file name.
I do not recommend doing that.
You can just hit enter.
Next up they ask you for a passphrase which we're not going to use.
I'm going to hit enter for no passphrase then I need to confirm the passphrase.
So I'll just hit enter again and right here we get a little message that our S-sh key was properly created
and that it was indeed saved in our folder.
You can see that right here with this in place I can now cycle back through my previous commands running
that last command.
And what do I get I get ID underscore RSA and I get the ID underscore RSA a pub file the RSA file contains
the private key.
This is the key you should never give to anyone it lives on your machine and your machine only if the
DOT pugged file that is the public file.
This one is the one you're going to give to third party services like get hub or Heroku which you'll
be doing in the next several videos.
Now that our keys are generated the last thing we need to do is start up the S-sh agent and add this
key so it knows that it exists.
We're going to do this by running two commands.
First up we're going to run evil then we're going to open some quotes inside of here we'll use the dollar
sign and open and close some parentheses just like this.
And inside of our parentheses we're going to type S-sh hyphen agent space with the flag.
This is going to start up the SS agent program and it's also going to print the process id to confirm
it is indeed running.
And right here we get Agent PD 1 6 5 4 7 the process ID is obviously going to be different as long as
you get something back like this.
You are good to go.
Next up we have to tell the S-sh agent where this file lives we're going to do that using S-sh hyphen.
And this takes the path to our private key file which we have in the user directory forward Slashdot
S-sh forward slash ID underscore RSA.
When I run this I should get a message like identity added.
This means that the local machine now knows about this public private key pair and it will try to use
these credentials when it communicates with a third party service like get hub.
Now that we have this in place we are ready to configure get hub.
We're going to make an account set it up and it will come back here and test that things are working
as expected.
And now let's head into the browser and go to get hub dot com here we'll be able to log into our existing
account or create a new one if you need a new one.
Fill out this form if you have an existing one.
Go ahead and sign an above.
Take a moment to pause the video until you see the screen that I see here.
This is your get hub dashboard.
When you're done go ahead and click play
all right I'm going to assume that you're seeing your dashboard from here we're going to navigate into
these settings over here about the profile picture go down to settings and in there we're going to go
to the S-sh page which is available under S-sh and g.p keys.
From here we can add that public key letting get hub know that we want to communicate using S-sh.
I'm going to add the new S-sh key and you need to do two things.
One give it a name and the name can be anything you like.
I usually use one that uniquely identifies my computer since I have a couple.
I'm going to use MacBook Pro just like this.
Next up we need to grab the contents of that ID.
RSA pub file that contains the information that you get how needs in order to securely communicate between
our machine and their machines.
We can grab this using a few different methods over in the browser we have that adding a new S-sh key
to your get help account article.
This contains a command you can use to copy the contents of that file to your clipboard from right inside
of the terminal.
Now obviously it is different for Mac Windows and Linux.
So go ahead and run the command for your operating system.
You could also go ahead and open it up with a regular text editor and copy the contents of the file.
It doesn't matter how you do it.
All that matters is you do.
I'm going to use the P.B. copy command which is available only on OS X.
I'm going to move into the terminal and I'm going to run it this copies the contents of the file to
the clipboard.
Now I can move back in to get help click the text area and paste it in.
Take a moment to copy the contents of the RSA pub paste it into the field.
It should start with S-sh hyphen RSA and it should end with that email you used.
Once you're done go ahead and click add S-sh.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knocked out.
And when you're done click play
all right I'm going to assume at this point you have that S-sh key added to get a job.
Now we can go ahead and test that things are working by running one command from the terminal.
Once again this command can be executed from anywhere on your machine.
You don't need to be in your project folder to do this.
We're going to use S-sh which tries to make a connection.
We're going to use the flag followed by the you are.
We want to connect to get at it get hub dot com.
This is going to test our connection.
It's going to make sure that the S-sh keys are properly set up and we can securely communicate with
get help.
When I run the command I get a message saying that the authenticity of the host get how BCom can't be
established.
We know that we want to communicate with dot com.
We're expecting that communication to happen so we can go ahead and hit yes.
From here we get a message from the get hub servers.
Hi Andrew J Mead which is my username you should see your username here.
We have successfully authenticated but how does NOT provide Schale access if you are seeing this message
then you are done.
You're ready to create your first repository and push your code up.
Now if you're not seeing this message something went wrong along the way.
Maybe the S-sh key wasn't generated correctly or it's not getting recognized by yet.
Go ahead and open a question in the Q&amp;A for this lecture.
I would be happy to debug.
I know this can be a real burden.
It's pretty tricky to set up if you're seeing this message.
What we're going to do is move in to get hub go back to the home page and we're going to create a new
repository.
Right here we have our new repository button.
All we need to do is give it a name.
I'm going to call this one node hyphen course to web server.
Once you have an end you could give it an optional description and you can pick whether you want to
go with a public or private repository.
Now private repositories do put you on a seven dollar plan.
I do recommend that if you're creating projects with companies.
In this case though we're creating pretty simple projects and it doesn't really matter if someone else
finds the code.
So I'm going to go ahead and use a public repository by clicking that option.
Once you have those two things filled out you can click Create repository and you're going to get brought
to your repository page and it's giving you a little set up because currently there is no code to view.
So it's giving you a few instructions depending on which situation you're in.
The first one is for creating a new repository.
We don't need that.
And the last one is for importing our code from some other you are Alloa we're not going to do what
we have is an existing repository and we want to push it from the command line.
We're going to run these two commands from inside of our project.
The first one adds a new remote to our Get repository remotes.
Let get know which third party you are else you want to sync up with.
Maybe I want to push my code to get help to communicate with my coworkers.
Maybe I also want to be able to push up to Heroku to deploy my app.
That means you would want two remotes.
In our case we're just going to add one so I'm going to copy this you r l move into the terminal paste
it and hit enter.
Now that we have our get remote and we can go ahead and run that second command this second command
which will be using extensively throughout the course is going to take our code and push it up to get
hub in the terminal we can copy and paste the code run the command and right here we can see everything
went great.
We were able to successfully write all of our data up to get up and if we go back into the browser and
refresh the page we're no longer going to see the set up instructions.
Instead we're going to see our repository kind of like a treeview here I can see we have our server
J S file which is great.
I don't see the logfile or node modules which is good because we ignored that.
I have my public directory.
Everything works really really well.
We also have issue tracking poll requests.
You can create a wiki which lets you set up instructions for your repository.
There's a lot of really great features that get hub has to offer.
There are entire courses dedicated to using get hub.
So I'd recommend checking one of those out we're going to be using just the very basic features over
here.
You can see we have one commit and if you click that one commit button you can actually go to the commit
page and here we see the initial commit message that we typed when we made that commit.
This is going to let us keep track of all of our code revert if we make unwanted changes and manage
our repository.
Now though we have our code pushed up.
We are done in the next video we're going to look at how we can communicate with Heroku to deploy our
code.
Then after that we'll look at some real world workflows for creating new commits pushing to get hub
and deploying to Heroku by the end of this section you'll be a master at the process so fear not as
long as you're able to see your code here then you are all set up.
You'll never need to touch those S-sh keys again.
Stay tuned.
I will see you next time.