In this video you're going to deploy your node app live to the web using Heroku.
By the end you'll have the you are and you can get anybody and they'll be able to go to that you are
all in their browser to view the application.
We're going to do this via Heroku Heroku is a Web site.
It's a web app for managing web applications that are hosted in the cloud.
It's a really great service.
They make it almost effortless to create new apps deploy your apps update apps and add cool add ons
things like logging an error tracking all of that is built in.
Now Heroku like a good hub does not require a credit card to sign up and there is a free tier which
we'll be using.
They have paid plans for just about everything but we can get away with the free tier for everything.
We'll be doing in this course to kick things off.
We're going to open up the browser and go to Heroku dot com here and we can go ahead and sign up for
a new account.
Take a quick moment to either log into your existing one or sign up for a new one.
I'm going to go ahead and log in to show you the dashboard.
I want you to pause the video go through that sign up process and once you see the dashboard you can
go ahead and click play.
Now your dashboard is going to look something like this although there might be a greeting telling you
to create a new application.
You can go ahead and ignore that.
I have a bunch of apps.
You won't have these.
That is perfectly fine.
Just take a moment to create your account log in and when you see something like this go ahead and click
click.
At this point I'm going to assume that you have a Heroku account and that you were able to log in.
And this is great because the next thing we're going to do is install the Heroku command line tools.
This is going to let us create apps deploy apps open apps and do all sorts of really cool stuff from
the terminal without having to come into the webapp that's going to save us time and make development
a lot easier.
We can grab that download by going to toolbelt doc Heroku dot com here we're able to grab the installer
from whatever platform you happen to be running on.
I'm going to go ahead and grab mine for Mac.
I'm going to start the download.
It's a really small download so it should happen pretty quickly once it's done we can go ahead and run
through the process.
This is a simple installer where you just click next.
There is no need to customize anything.
You don't have to enter any specific information about your Heroku account.
I'm going to go ahead and complete the installer and all this really is going to do is give us a new
command from the terminal that we can execute.
And before we can do that we do have to log in locally in the terminal and that's exactly what we're
going to do next.
So take a moment to pause the video and get to the step where the installation was completed successfully.
When you're done you can go ahead and click play.
By now I'm going to assume that you have installed the Heroku toolbelt for your operating system.
Now what I'd like you to do is go ahead and start up the terminal.
If you already have it running you might need to restart it in order for your operating system to recognize
the new command.
You can test that it got installed properly by running Heroku hyphen hyphen help when you run this command.
You're going to see that it's installing the CLID for the first time and then you're going to get all
of the help information.
This will tell you what commands you have access to and exactly how they work.
Now we are going to need to log in to the Heroku account locally and this process is pretty simple.
Here we have all of the commands available.
And one of them happens to be log in we can run Heroku log in just like this to start the process.
I'm going to go ahead and run the log in command.
And now we just use the email and password that we had set up before I'm going to type in my email.
That I'm going to go ahead and type in my password.
Typing is hidden because it's secure and when I do that you see logged in as Andrew.
Joseph Mead shows up and this is fantastic.
And now we're logged in and we're able to successfully communicate between our machines command line
and the Heroku servers.
This means we can get started creating and deploying applications.
Next up I'm going to use the clear command to clear the terminal output.
And now we're going to go ahead and get our S-sh key on Heroku.
Kind of like what we did with get up only this time we can do it via the command line so it's going
to be a lot easier in order to add our local keys to Heroku.
We're going to run Heroku space keys colon.
And this is going to scan our S-sh directory and add the key up here you can see it found a key id RSA
pub file.
Would you like to upload it to Heroku.
Yes I would.
Excellent.
Now we have R-KY uploader that is all it took.
Much easier than it was to configure with get up from here we can use the Heroku keys command to print
all of the keys currently on our account and we could always go ahead and remove them using Heroku keys
call and remove followed by the e-mail related to that key.
In this case we're going to keep the Heroku key that we have.
Next up we can test our connection using S-sh with the flag get at Heroku dot com.
This is going to communicate with the Heroku servers and right here you can see it's asking that same
question authenticity of the host can't be established.
Do you want to continue.
Yes.
Now when you run that command you're going to get a lot of cryptic output.
What you're looking for is authentication succeeded and then in parentheses public key if things did
not go well you're going to see the permission denied message with public key in parentheses.
In this case the authentication was successful which means we are good to go.
I'm going to go ahead and run clear one more time.
Clearing the terminal output.
Now we can turn our attention towards the application code because before we can deploy to Heroku we
are going to need to make two changes to the code.
These are things that Heroku expects your app to have in place in order to run properly because Heroku
does a lot of things automatically which means you have to have some basic stuff set up for Heroku to
work.
Now I promise it's not too complex.
Some really simple changes a couple of one liners.
First up in server J ass down at the very bottom of the file we have the port.
Our app listens to statically coded inside of server.
Yes we need to make this dynamic which means we want to use a variable.
We're going to be using an environment variable that Heroku was going to set Heroku will tell your app
which port to use because that port will change as you deploy your app which means that we're going
to be using that environment variable so we don't have to swap out our code every time we want to deploy.
That would be a super big pain and would actually be impossible with environment variables.
Heroku can set a variable on the operating system your node app can read that variable and it can use
it as the port.
Now all machines have environment variables.
You can actually view the ones on your machine by running NVI on Linux or OSX or the set command on
Windows.
And what you're going to get when you do that is a really long list of key value pairs.
And this is all environment variables are here we have a log name environment variables set.
Andrew I have a home environment variable set to my home directory all sorts of environment variables
throughout my operating system.
One of these that Heroku is going to set is called port which means we need to go ahead grab that port
variable and use it here instead of 3000 up at the very top of the file.
I'd like you to make a constant called port and this is going to store the port that we're going to
use for the app.
Now the first thing we're going to do is grab a port from process dot EMV process.
Envy is an object that stores all of our environment variables as key value pairs.
We're looking for one the Heroku is going to set called Port awesome.
This is going to work great for Heroku But when we run the app locally the port environment variable
is not going to exist.
So we're going to go ahead and set a default using the OR operator right here.
If process.
Ian B-cup port does not exist.
We'll set port equal to 3000 instead.
Excellent.
Now we have an app that's configured to work with Heroku and to still run locally just like it did before.
All we have to do is take the port variable and use that down below instead of 3000 right here.
I'm going to reference port and down below inside of our message.
I'm going to swap it out for template strings.
I'll paste the old text back in.
And now I can replace 3000 with the injected port variable which is going to change over time.
With this in place we have now fixed the first problem with our app.
And if I run node server from the terminal like we did earlier I'm still going to get the exact same
message.
Server is up on port 3000.
So your app will still work locally as expected.
Next up we have to specify a script in package dot Jason inside a package.
Jason you might have noticed we have a script object and there we have a test script.
This gets set by default for NPM.
We can create all sorts of scripts inside of here that do whatever we like.
A script is nothing more than a command that we run from the terminal.
So I can take this command node server dock jackass and turn into a script instead.
And that's exactly what we're going to do right here.
We're going to go ahead and add a new script.
The script needs to be called start.
This is a very specific and built in script and we're going to set it equal to the command that starts
our app.
In this case it's going to be node space server.
Yes this is necessary because when Heroku tries to start our app it's not going to run a node with your
file name because it doesn't know what your file name is called.
Instead it's going to run the start script and the start script will be responsible for doing the proper
thing.
In this case booting up that server file.
Now we can run our app using that start script from the terminal by using NPM start just like this.
When I do that we get a little output related to NPM and then we get server is up on port three thousand.
And if we visit the app in the browser everything works exactly as it did before.
The big difference is that we are now already for Heroku.
We could also run the test script using from the terminal NPM test.
This is something that we'll be doing a little later in the course.
For now we have no tests specified and that is expected.
The next step in the process is going to be to make that commit and then we can finally start getting
it up on the web from the terminal.
We're going to use some of those get commands we explored earlier in this section first up and get status.
When I run get status we have something a little new instead of new files we have modified files.
Here we have a modified package.
Jason File and we have a modified server doc Jap's file.
These are not going to be committed if we were to run and get commit just yet we still have to use GET
add.
And what we're going to do is run get ADD with the dot as the next argument dot is going to add every
single thing showing up and get status to the next commit.
Now I only recommend using the syntax of everything you have listed here are things you actually want
to commit.
And in our case that is indeed what we want.
If I run get ADD and then rerun it get status.
I can now see what is going to be committed next.
Under the changes to be committed Hetter.
Here we have our packaged Jason File and the server data file.
Now we can go ahead and make that commit.
I'm going to run and get commit with the flags so we can specify our message and a good message for
this commit would be something like set up start script and Heroku port.
Excellent.
Now we can go ahead and run that command which is going to make that commit.
And now we can go ahead and push that up to get hub using get push and we can leave off the Orjan remote
because the origin is the default remote.
I'm going to go ahead and run.
Push.
This is going to push it up to get help.
And now we are ready to actually create the app push our code up and view it over in the browser.
The next step in the process is going to be to run a command called Heroku create from the terminal
Heroku create needs to get executed from inside of your application just like we run our get commands
when I run your Roku create a couple things are going to happen first.
It's going to make a real new application over in the Heroku web app.
It's also going to add a new remote to your get repository.
Now remember we have an origin remote which points to our Get hub repository.
We're going to have a Heroku remote which points to our Heroku get repository.
When we deploy to the Heroku repository Heroku is going to see that it's going to take the changes and
it's going to deploy them into the web.
When we run Heroku create all of that happens.
Now we do still have to push up to this you are all in order to actually do the deploying process.
And we can do that using get push
followed by Heroku the brand new remote that was just added because we ran Heroku create.
Now pushing this time around is going to go through the normal process and then you're going to start
seeing some logs.
And these are logs coming back from Heroku letting you know how your app is deploying.
It's going through the entire process showing you what happens along the way.
As you can see that took about 10 seconds and at the very end we have some success messages.
The app was launched successfully right here.
It also verified that the app was deployed successfully and that it did indeed pass from here.
We actually have a u r l we can visit that you are Ellas right here.
We can take it copy and paste it in the browser.
What I'm going to do instead is use a command Heroku open Heroku.
Open is going to open up the Heroku app in the default browser.
When I run this is going to switch over to Chrome and right here we get our application showing up just
as expected.
I can switch between pages and everything works just like it did locally.
Now we have a U R L and this u r l was given to us by Heroku.
This is the default way Heroku generates app you are else if you have your own domain registration company
you can go ahead and configure its DNS to point to this application.
This is going to let you use a custom You are Alphie or Heroku app you have to refer to the specific
instructions for your domain registrar in order to do that but it can indeed be done.
Now that we have this in place we have successfully deployed our node applications live to Heroku.
And this is just fantastic.
In order to do this all we had to do was make a commit to change our code and push it up to a new get
remote.
It could not be easier to deploy our code.
You could also manage your application by going back over to the Heroku dashboard.
If you give it a refresh you should see that brand new you are out somewhere down below.
Remember mine was sleepy retreat yours is going to be something else.
If I scroll down I have sleepy retreat right here.
I can click it and I can view the app page here we can do a lot of configuration we can manage the activity
and access so we can collaborate with others.
We have metrics we have resources all sorts of really cool stuff with this in place we are now done
with our basic deploying video in the next video.
Your challenge is going to be to go through that process again.
You're going to add some changes to the node app you're going to commit them deploy them and view them
live in the web.
That's all coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time