Hello and welcome to Section 7 testing your node applications and this section we're going to look at
how we can test our code to make sure it's working as expected.
Now if you set up test cases for other languages then you know how hard it can be to get started.
You have to set up the actual test infrastructure and then you have to write your individual test cases.
Every time I didn't test an application it was because the set up process and the tools available to
me were such a burden.
Then you dig around for information on line and you get really simple examples but not examples for
testing real world things like asynchronous code or express applications.
We're going to be doing all of that in this section.
I'm going to give you a very simple setup for testing and writing your test cases.
We're going to look at the best tools available.
So you'll actually be excited to write those test cases and see all of those green checkmarks.
We're going to be testing from here on out as well.
So let's go ahead and dive in looking at how we can test some code