In this video you're going to create your very first test cases so you can test that your code is working
as expected by adding automatic testing to our project will be able to verify that a function does what
it says it'll do if we make a function that's supposed to add two numbers together we can automatically
verify it's doing that.
And if we have a function that's supposed to fetch a user from the database we can make sure it's doing
that as well.
Now to get started in this video we're going to look at the very basics of setting up a testing suite
inside of a node J.S. project.
We'll be testing a real world function and will be a challenge for you to test something as well in
order to get started.
We are going to make a directory to store our code for this section.
I'm going to make one on the desktop using m k d i r and I'll call this directory node hyphen tests.
Then I'm going to see the inside of it node hyphen tests so I can go ahead and run and PM in it.
We are going to be installing modules and this is going to require a package does Jason File.
I'm going to run NPM in it using the default values for everything simply clicking enter throughout
every single step.
Now once that package that Jason file is generated we can go ahead and open up the directory inside.
Adam it's on the desktop and it's called node hyphen tests from here.
We're ready to actually define a function that we want to test.
The goal in this video is to learn how to set up testing for node project.
So the actual functions we'll be testing are going to be pretty trivial but it will help illustrate
exactly how to set up our tests to get started.
Let's go ahead and make a fake module that will have some functions and we'll test those functions in
the route of the project.
I'm going to make a brand new directory and I'm going to call this directory tildes.
We can assume this will store some utility functions like adding a number to another number or stripping
out white spaces from a string anything kind of hodgepodge.
That doesn't really belong in any specific location.
I'm going to make a new file in the utility folder called utility dot J.S. and this is a similar pattern
to what we did when we created the weather and location directory in our weather app.
You're probably wondering why we have a folder and a file with the same name.
I promise that will be clear in just a second.
When we start testing now before we can write our first test case to make sure something works we need
something to test.
And I'm going to make a very basic function that takes two numbers and adds them together will create
an outer function by setting module.
Exports don't add equal to an arrow function.
Now that arrow function is going to take two arguments a and b and inside of the function where it is
going to return the value a plus b.
Nothing too complex here.
In essence we just have one expression inside of our arrow function and we want to return it.
We can actually use the arrow function expression syntax which lets us at our expression right here
A plus B and it's going to be implicitly returned.
There's no need to explicitly add a return keyword on it to the function.
And now that we have you tells Yes ready to go let's explore testing.
We're going to be using a framework called Moka in order to set up our test suite.
And this is going to let us configure our individual test cases and also run all of our test files.
This is going to be really important for creating and running tests.
The goal here is to make testing simple.
And we're going to use Moka to do just that.
Now that we have a file and a function we actually want to test.
Let's go ahead and explore how to create and run a test suite.
We're going to be doing this using these super popular testing framework Moka Moka which you can find
in your browser at Moka J.S. dot org is a fantastic framework for creating and running test suites.
It's super popular and they're page right here has all the information you'd ever want to know about
setting it up configuring it and all the cool bells and whistles it has included.
If you scroll down just a little bit you'll be able to see a table of contents.
Here you can explore everything.
Moka has to offer will be covering most of it in this section but for anything we don't cover I do want
to make you aware.
You can always learn about it here.
Now that we've explored the Moka documentation page let's go ahead and install it and start using it
over in the terminal.
I'm going to install Moka First up I am going to clear the terminal output and then we can go ahead
and install it using NPM install.
When you use NPM install you can also use the shortcut NPM.
I this has the exact same effect.
I'm going to use NPM.
I with Moka specifying the version at three point zero point zero.
This is the most recent version of the library as of this filming.
Now we do want to save this into the package that Jason File previously we have used the same flag but
we're going to talk about a new flag right here called Save hyphen dev save.
Dev is going to save this package for development purposes only.
And that's exactly what Moka is going to be for.
We don't actually need Moka to run our app on a service like Heroku.
We just need Moka locally on our machine to test our code.
When you use the save death flag it installs the module much the same way.
But if you explore package drop Jason you'll see things are a little different.
Over inside of our package that Jason file instead of a dependencies attribute we have a dev dependencies
attribute in there we have Moka with the version number as the value dev dependencies are fantastic
because they're not going to be installed on Heroku but they will be installed locally.
This will keep the Heroku boot times really really quick.
It won't need to install modules that it's not going to actually need.
We'll be installing Boll's dev dependencies and dependencies in most of our projects from here on out.
Now that we have Moka installed we can go ahead and create a test file over in the utils folder.
We're going to make a new file this file is going to store our test cases.
We're not going to store test cases in utilities.
Yes this is going to be our application code.
Instead we're going to make a file called utils dot test.
Us when we use this test.
Jeff's extension we're basically telling our app that this is going to store our test cases and when
Moka goes through our app for tests to run it should run any file with this extension.
Now we have a test file.
The only thing left to do is create a test case a test case is a function that runs some code and if
things go well great the test is considered to have passed and if things do not go well the test is
considered to have failed.
We can create a new test case using it.
It is a function provided by moka.
We're going to be running our project to test files through Moka so there's no reason to import it or
do anything like that.
We simply call it just like this now.
It lets us to find a new test case and it takes two arguments.
First up we're going to have a string description of what exactly the test is doing.
If we're testing that the outer function works we might have something like it should add two numbers.
Notice here that it plays into the sentence.
It should read like this.
It should add two numbers describes exactly what the test is going to verify.
This is called behavior driven development or BDD and that's the principles that Moka was built on.
Now we've set up the test string.
The next thing to do is add a function of the second argument inside this function we're going to add
the code that tests that the add function works as expected.
This means that will probably call ad and check that the value that comes back is the appropriate value
given the two numbers passed in.
That means we do need to import the Eutelsat file up above.
I'm going to create a constant called you tills setting equal to the return result from requiring you
tills.
I'm using forward slash.
Since we are going to be requiring a local file it's in the same directory so I can simply type Patels
right here without the J.S. extension.
Now that we have the details a library loaded in inside of the callback we can call it let's make a
variable to store the return results.
I'm going to call this one results and we'll set it equal to you tills and don't add passing in two
numbers.
Let's go ahead and use something like 33 plus 11.
We would expect it to get 40 for back.
Now at this point we do have some code inside of our test suite so we can go ahead and run it and we're
going to do that by configuring that test script we looked at in the last section inside a package.
Jason currently the test script simply prints a message to the screen saying that no tests exist but
we're going to do instead is call Moka right here.
We're going to be calling Moka passing in as the one and only argument in the actual files we want to
test and we can use the globbing pattern to specify multiple files.
In this case we'll be using star star to look in every single directory and we're looking for a file
called utils dot test dot J.
Yes.
Now this is a very specific pattern it's not going to be particularly useful.
Instead we can swap out the file name with a star as well.
Now we're looking for any file in the project that has a file name ending in dot test dot Yes and this
is exactly what we want from here.
We can run our test suite by saving package adjacent and moving over to the terminal.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output and then we can run our test script using NPM test
when we run this.
We're actually going to be executing that Moka command.
It's going to go off.
It's going to fetch all of our test files.
It's going to run all of them and print the results right here.
Here we can see we have a green checkmark next to our test.
Should add two numbers then down below we have a little summary one passing test and it happened in
eight milliseconds.
Now in our case we don't actually assert anything about the number that comes back.
It could be seven hundred and we wouldn't care.
The test is always going to pass to make a test fail.
What we have to do is throw an error that means right here we can throw a new error and we pass into
the constructor function whatever message we want to use as the error.
In this case I could say something like a value not correct.
Now with this in place I can save the test file and rerun things over from the terminal by rerunning
NPM test.
And when I do that now we have 0 tests passing and we have one test failing Double-O we can see the
one test is I should add two numbers and we get our error message value not correct when we throw a
new error the test fails.
And that's exactly what we want to do for ad right here.
I'm going to go ahead and create an if statement if the response value is not equal to 44.
That means we have a problem on our hands and we're going to throw an error inside of here.
I can throw a new air and I'm going to use a template string as our message string because I do want
to use the value that comes back in and the error message I'm going to say expected 44 comma but got.
Then I'll inject the actual value whatever happens to come back.
Now in our case everything is going to line up great but what if the add method wasn't working correctly.
Overing you tale's we can simulate this by simply tacking on another edition adding on something like
22.
I'm going to save the file or rerun the test suite.
And now we get an error message expected 44 but got 66 this error message is fantastic.
It lets us know that something is going wrong with the test and that even tells us exactly what we got
back and what we expected.
This is going to let us go into the add function look for errors and hopefully fix them.
Now if we were to rerun the test suite with the appropriate add function all of our tests should be
passing and right here we get just that creating test cases does it need to be something super complex.
Here you can see we have a simple test case that tests a simple function.
Now for a challenge we're going to create a new function and you're going to be responsible for adding
a test case that asserts it works as expected.
Let's go ahead and create a function that squares a number and returns the result.
We're going to define that over in you tildes module ADOT exports dot square we'll set that equal to
an arrow function that takes in one number X and we're going to return x times x x times X just like
this.
Now we have this brand new function Square and it's going to be your job to create a new test case that
makes sure square works as expected.
Overing you tills adcom test.
Yes down below you're going to call it again with something like it should square a number then you're
going to call the utility ADOT square method passing in a number of your choice and you're going to
store the result in a variable and then you'll use an IF statement to check if it's not what you expect
it to be.
If it's not you can throw a new error printing a little message like we do here.
Now when you create that task you should be able to run the test suite and you'll see that everything
works as expected because currently the utility function is defined correctly.
We just do X times x.
I want you to mess up square doing something like X times x plus one or any other computation that's
going to cause an incorrect result to be returned.
Then you can rerun your test suite and your new test should fail if it fails then you are done the challenge.
You can fix the square function make your test pass again and then you can go ahead and click play.
So take a moment create that new test case mess up the square function fix the square function make
sure everything works as expected and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
I hope you were able to create that test case and see it pass.
Then you were able to mess things up watching it fail.
I'm going to get started in details test file by adding a new call to it to make the new test case inside
of here.
We're going to add our two arguments the string which will fill out in just a second and the callback
function inside the string.
I'm going to create our message.
It should square a number
and inside of the callback function we can actually go ahead and call Square.
Now I do want to create a variable to store the results so I can check that the result is what I expect
it to be.
Then I can call you tildes square passing in a number I'm going to go with three in this case which
means I should expect nine to come back down below.
I can have an if statement.
If the result does not equal nine then we're going to go ahead and throw a message because things went
wrong.
We can throw an error using throw new error passing in whatever message we like we can use a regular
string but I always prefer using a template string so we can inject values easily.
I'll say something like expected 9 comma but got followed by the value.
That's not correct in this case that's stored in the response variable.
Now I can go ahead and save this test case and run the test suite from the terminal using the up arrow
key and the Enter key.
I can rerun the last command.
And what do we get.
We get two tests passing should add two numbers and should square a number of both have check marks
next to them and we ran both tests in just 14 milliseconds which is fantastic.
Now the next thing I want you to do is mess up the square function to make sure your test fails when
the number is not correct.
I'm going to go ahead and add one on to the result which is going to cause the test to fail.
Then I can rerun things over from the terminal and we should see the error message and right here we
do expect a 9 but got 10.
This is fantastic.
We now have a test suite capable of testing both the add function and the square function.
I'm going to remove that plus one and we are done.
We now have a very very basic test suite that we could execute with moka.
Currently we have two tests and to create those tests we use the method provided by Moka in the next
several videos we'll be exploring more methods that Moka gives us and we'll also be looking at better
ways to do our assertions instead of manually creating them.
We'll be using an assertion library to help with the heavy lifting.
That is all coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you soon.