Before you write even one more test case I want to set you up with an automatic way to rerun your test
suite when you change either your test code or your application code.
We're going to be doing that with no man.
Now Previously we used gnomon like this we would type gnomon and we would pass in a file like apt.
Yes whenever any code in our app changed it would rerun the app J js file as a node application.
What we can actually do is specify any command in the world we want to run when our files change.
This means we can rerun NPM tests when the files change.
To do this we're going to use the x E C flag.
This flag tells gnomon that we're going to specify a command to run.
And it might not necessarily be a node file right here in quotes.
We can specify that command.
It's going to be NPM test.
This is Andrew with an update if you are using Windows remember to use double quotes here.
With this in place we can now run the gnomon command.
It's going to kick off for the first time running our test suite.
Here we see we have two tests passing.
I'm going to go ahead into the app and make a change to one of the functions.
So it fails.
I'll add three or four on to the result for ADD.
It automatically restarts over here and now we see that we have a test suite where one test passes and
one test fails I can always go ahead and undo that error save the file and the test suite is automatically
going to rerun.
This is going to make testing your application that much easier.
You won't have to switch to the terminal and rerun the NPM test command every time you make a change
to your application.
Now we have a command that we can run.
I'm going to shut down gnomon and use the up arrow key to show it again right here and we can actually
move this into a script inside a package.
Jason inside a package that Jason we're going to make a new script right after the test script.
Now we've used the start script and the test script and these are built in.
We're going to create a custom one right here called Test hyphen watch and we can run the test watch
script to kick things off inside of here we're going to have the exact same command we ran from the
terminal.
That means we're going to be running gnomon.
We'll be using that.
Yes.
See flag.
And inside of quotes we're going to be running NPM test and now that we have this in place we can run
the script from the terminal as opposed to having to type out this command every single time we want
to start up the auto test suite.
A quick update.
I recommend using the following test watch script.
It's a little more cross OS friendly.
What we have inside of package Jason currently is going to work on OS X and Linux it will also work
on Heroku which uses Linux but it's not going to work on Windows.
The following script the script you see here will as you can see here we're escaping the quotes surrounding
NPM test and we're using double quotes which as we know are the only quotes supported by Windows.
This script will remove any errors you're seeing something like NPM cannot be found which you will get
if you wrap NPM test in single quotes and run the script on Windows.
So use the following script for cross OS compatibility.
To run a script with a custom name like test watch over in the terminal.
All we need to do is run and PM run followed by the script name test hyphen watch.
If I do this it's going to start things off.
We're going to get our test suite and it's still waiting for changes which is fantastic.
Now every time you start the test suite you can simply use NPM run test watch that's going to start
up the test watch script which starts up gnomon every time a change happens in your project.
It's going to rerun NPM test showing the results of the test suite to the screen and that is it for
this one.
Now that we have a way to automatically restart our test suite Let's go ahead and get back into the
specifics of testing in that node.
Stay tuned.
We'll see you next time