Two videos ago we made two test cases to verify that and Hotels.com at an and you tills square method
work as expected.
And we did that and using an if condition if the value was not 44 that means something went wrong and
we threw an error in this video.
We're going to learn how to use an assertion library.
We're just going to take care of all of this code for us because as you'll see when we add more and
more tests the code is going to end up looking pretty similar and there's no reason to keep rewriting
it.
Assertion libraries let us make assertions about values whether it's about their type the value itself
whether an array contains an element all sorts of things like that.
They really are fantastic.
The one we're going to be using is called expect.
You can find it by going to Google and Googling them.
Jackson expect and this is the result we're looking for it's m Jackson's repository expect it is a fantastic
and super popular assertion library and this library is going to let us pass in value and make some
assertions about it.
If you scroll down past the introduction and the installation We'll talk about those later.
We can get down to an example right here.
We have our sessions Haueter and we have our first assertion to exist.
And this is going to verify that a value exists.
Down below we have an example we pass in a string to expect.
This is the value we want to make some assertions about in the context of our application.
That would be the response variable right here.
We want to assert that it is equal to 44 after we call expect.
We can start chaining on some assertion calls right.
Here we check if it does exist.
This would not throw an error because a string is indeed truth inside of javascript if we passed in
something like undefined which is not truthy to exist would fail.
It would throw an error and the test case would not pass.
Using these assertions we can make it really really easy to check the values in our tests without having
to write all of that code ourselves.
Let's go ahead and start exploring it.
First up I am going to install it inside of the terminal by running NPM install and the module name
itself is called expect.
And we're going to grab the most recent version.
At one point twenty point to Andrew here from the future with a very important update.
We expect the library has been donated to a different organization and the latest version which is the
twenty one point 1.0 is not backwards compatible with the version used here 1.2 zero point two.
So here's how we're going to work around that.
What I'd like you to do is install the version in the video that is 1 point to zero point two.
That's going to make sure you can go through the next several videos and I promise a little bit later
in the course I will have an upgrade video which I'm going to be filming in just a few minutes.
This upgrade video is going to show you how you can upgrade from expect 1 point to zero point two to
the latest version which would be the twenty one it is going to be important though that you do stick
with this expect version for now 1.2 0.2.
If you don't you are going to run into issues.
Don't worry though I will get you upgraded to the latest a little bit later in the course.
So let's go ahead and jump back into the video and I'll see you in a few sections when we upgrade to
the latest version.
And once again we'll be using the save death flag like we did with Moka because we do indeed want to
save this dependency and package that Jason.
But it's a dev dependency it's not required for the application to run whether it's on Heroku or some
other service.
I'm going to go ahead and install this dependency and then we can move over to the application checkout
package Jason.
And it looks great.
We have expect and we have Moka now inside of our utility test file.
We can kick things off by loading in the library and making our first assertions using expect up at
the very top of the file.
I'm going to load in the library creating a constant call expect and requiring require expect just like
this.
Now down below we can get started by swapping out this code with a call to expect instead.
Now as you saw over in the example we're going to start all of our assertions by calling expect as a
function passing in the value we want to make assertions about.
In this case that is the result variable.
Now we can assert all sorts of things.
In this case we want to assert that the value is equal to 44.
I'm going to go over to the documentation just to get you comfortable looking around and this is one
of those pieces of documentation you're going to come back to.
More so than anything else.
Most apps I use the same methods that I have them memorized but with expect there so many assertions
and they're so useful I find myself with this tab open quite a bit.
But we're going to use to make our assertion is to be this asserts that a value equals another value
and that's exactly what we want.
We assert that our value passed into expect equal another value using to be passing that value in as
the first argument back inside of atom.
We can go ahead and use this assertion dot to be.
And we're expecting the result variable to be number 44 just like this.
Awesome.
Now we have our test case and it should work exactly as it did down below to prove it does work I'm
going to move into the terminal and use clear to clear the terminal output.
And now we can run that test.
Watch script using NPM run test hyphen watch just like this.
I'm going to kick it off and right here we get our two tests passing just like they did before.
Now if I were to change 44 to some other value that would throw an error like 40 and I save the file.
We are going to get an error and the expect library is going to generate useful error messages for us.
It's saying that we expected 44 to be 40.
Clearly that's not the case.
So an error gets thrown.
I'm going to change this back to 44.
Save the file and all of our tests will pass.
Excellent.
Now we can also chain together multiple assertions.
For example we could assert that the value that comes back from ADD is a number that this can be done
using another assertion.
So let's head into the docs and take a look.
Inside of Crome we're going to scroll down through the docs list.
There's a lot of methods we'll be exploring some of them.
We're looking for this one to be a method that takes a strain.
This takes the string type and it uses the type of operator to assert that the value is of a certain
type.
Here we're expecting to be a number we can do that exact same thing over and our code inside of Adam
right after to be can change on another call to be a followed by the type.
This could be something like string.
It could be something like object or in our case it could be number.
Just like this.
I'm going to open up the terminal so we can see the result.
It's currently hidden save the file.
Our tests are going to rerun and we can see they're both passing.
If I were to use a different type something that was going to cause the test to fail we would get an
error message like this expected 44 to be a string.
This is really useful it's going to help us clean up our errors really quickly.
I'm going to change this back to number and we are good to go.
Now I'd like you to do the same thing for our test down below.
I want you to use expect to assert that the response is indeed the number 9 and that the type is a number
you're going to use the same two assertions we do up above.
Go ahead and swap this code out for calls to expect make those assertions.
Save the file and make sure both tests are still passing.
Pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play.
All right.
All you needed to do to get that done is first up delete the current code.
Since we're not going to be using that any more throughout the rest of the course we will never again
be throwing errors manually inside of our tests.
Instead we'll be using assertion libraries right here.
We're going to make some expectations about the result variable.
First up we're going to expect it to be the number 9 just like this.
I'm going to save the file and make sure the test passes and it does indeed pass.
Now we're also going to assert the type using to be a.
Here we're checking that the type of the return value from the square method is a number and when I
save the file we get both of our tests still passing which is fantastic.
Now this is just a small taste as to what I expect can do.
Let's go ahead and create a bogus test case that is going to explore a few more ways we can use expect.
We're not going to be testing an actual function we'll just play around with some assertions inside
of the callback.
I'm going to make a new test using it.
It should expect some values.
You can put whatever you want here it's not too important and we're going to pass in an arrow function
as our callback function.
Excellent.
Now as we've seen already one of the most fundamental assertions you're going to make is you're just
going to check for equality.
I want to check if something like the response variable equals something else like the number 44 inside
of expect we can also do the opposite.
We can expect that a value like 12 does not equal using two and not a B.
And then we can assert that a doesn't equal some other value like 11.
The two are equal.
So when I save the file over in the terminal.
All three tests should be passing.
If I set them equal to the same value it's not going to work as expected.
We're going to get an error expected 12 to not be 12.
Now to be and not to be.
Work great for numbers strings and booleans But if you're trying to compare arrays or objects they are
not going to work as expected and we can prove this.
I'm going to remove the current code by commenting it out.
I'll leave it around so we have it for later.
I'm going to expect an object with the name property set to Andrew with an uppercase a to b dot to be.
And I'm going to assert that it is another object where the name property is equal to Andrew.
Just like this to not be is going to work great for numbers strings and booleans but it's not going
to work for objects.
And we can prove this.
I'm going to comment out the current call and we're going to replace it with an expectation that an
object where the name property equals Andrew equals another object that looks exactly the same.
We're going to use to be just like we did up above.
Checking if it is the same as another object where name equals Andrew ASA.
Now when I go ahead and say this you might think the text is going to pass but it's not right here.
We see that we expected these two to be equal when objects are compared for equality using the triple
equals which is what to be uses.
They're not going to be the same because it's trying to see if they're the exact same object and they're
not.
We've created two separate objects with the same properties to check if these two are equal.
We're going to have to use something different.
It's called two equal if I say my file.
This is going to work.
It's going to rip into the object properties making sure they have the same ones the same thing goes
for two not equal.
This checks if two objects are not equal I'm going to go ahead and change the first object to have a
lower case A and Andrew.
And the test passes.
They are not equal.
This is how we do equality with our objects and arrays.
Now another really useful thing we have is to include this checks if an array or an object includes
some things.
Now it's an array.
We can check if it includes a certain item in the array.
If it's an object we can check if it includes certain properties.
Let's go ahead and run through an example of that right here.
We're going to expect that an array with the numbers 2 3 and 4 inside of it has inside of it the number
5 and we can do that using to include to include it takes the item.
In this case we're going to check if the array has 5 inside.
No clearly it doesn't.
So this test is going to fail.
We get the message we expected to 3:4 to include five that does not exist if we change this to a number
that does exist like two.
We're going to rerun the test suite and everything is going to work as expected.
Now along with to include we have to exclude like this.
This is going to check if something does not exist like the number one which is not in the array.
If I run this assertion the test passes the same two methods to include and to exclude work with objects
as well.
We can play with that right on the next line.
I'm going to expect that the falling object has something on it.
Let's go ahead and create an object that has a name property.
Go ahead and set it equal to your first name.
Well also make an age property.
I'm going to set that equal to my age and we'll set a location property I'm going to set that equal
to my location.
Now let's say we want to make some assertions about particular properties not necessarily the entire
object.
We can use to include to assert that the object has some properties and that those property values equals
the value we pass in.
For example the age.
Let's say we only care about the age we can assert that the object has an age property equal to 25.
By typing this code it doesn't matter that there is a name property the name property could be any value
that is relevant in this assertion.
Now if the value is not correct like it's 23.
This test is going to fail.
We expected the age property to be 23 but it was indeed 25.
So the test fails.
Same thing goes with to exclude to exclude.
Here we can save our test files this checks if the object does not have a property age equal to 23.
It does indeed not have that.
So the test passes.
This is just a quick taste as to what I expect can do for a full list of features I recommend diving
through the documentation.
There is a ton of other assertions you can use things like checking if a number is greater than another
number if a number is less than or equal to another number.
All sorts of math related operations are included as well.
Now let's go ahead and wrap things up with a challenge that requires you to use some of this knowledge
over in your tills.
Yes we can make a new function one that you'll be testing.
Module datt exports dot.
Set name.
Set name is going to take two arguments.
It's going to take a user object some fictitious user object with some generic properties and it's going
to take a full name as a string.
The job of set name is going to be to rip apart full name into two parts.
The first name and the last name by splitting it on the space we're going to go ahead and set the two
properties first name and last name and return the user object will fill out the function together.
You're going to be responsible for writing the test case.
The first thing we're going to do is split the name into a names array var names is going to be that
array.
It'll have two values assuming there's only one space inside of the name.
For now that's the assumption we're assuming someone types their first name space their last name.
I know that doesn't work with every single name but it'll get us a bye.
For now I'm going to go ahead and set this equal to full name dot split and we're going to split on
the space so I'm going to pass in an empty string with a space inside of it as the value to split.
Now we have a names array where the first item is the first name and the last item is the last name.
So we can start updating the user object user ADOT first name is going to equal the first item in the
names array names array.
And we're going to grab the index of the 0 which is the first item and we'll do something similar for
last name user and last name equals the second item from the names array.
Now we're all done we have the names set and we can go ahead and return the user object using return
user.
Just like this I forgot my equal sign.
I'm going to go ahead and add that right here.
Awesome.
Over inside of the tills test file we can now kick things off.
I'm going to leave a comment for what I'd like you to do.
I'm going to comment out.
It should expect some values.
Handler this is pretty great for documentation.
You can always explore it later if you forget how things work.
But for now it's not necessary.
We're going to create a new test that should verify first and last names are set.
Awesome.
You're going to be responsible for creating a user object on that user object.
I want you to set some properties like age and location then you're going to pass that variable user
into the set name method that's going to be the first argument defined right here.
You're also going to pass in a string the string with your first name followed by a space followed by
your last name then you're going to go ahead and get the result back and you're going to make some assertions
about it.
I want you to assert that the returning object includes using to include assert.
It includes first name and last name with proper values.
So if I pass in as my full name and you Space me and I would expect the first name to be Andrew and
the last name to be Mead So pause the video.
Play around with this one.
Make the test case.
Make the user object.
Call the function and make our assertion using to include.
I also want you to verify that the type is indeed an object using to be a
how do you do.
Hopefully you are able to get that done if you ran into any problems that is perfectly fine.
You're really new to testing.
We just made our third test so it's ok if things did not go as planned.
Right here I'm going to call it to make the new test case.
We're going to be testing it should set first name and last name inside of here we can now provide our
second argument which is going to be our callback function.
I'm going to set that to an arrow function.
And now we can make that user object I talked about the user object is going to have a few properties.
I'm going to add something like location setting that equal to Philadelphia and I'll set an age property
setting that equal to 25.
Now we can go ahead and call the method we defined over and Eutelsat.
J.S. set name I'm going to do that on the next line.
Creating a variable called response to store the response and then set that equal to you tildes dot
set name passing in the two arguments to the user object and the full name.
Right here I'll provide Andrew space meat.
Now at this point if the result should be what we expect we should have that first name and last name
property we should have the location property and we should have the age property.
Now if you know a lot about javascript you might know that objects are passed by reference.
So the user variable has actually been updated as well.
That is expected both the user and response are going to have the exact same value.
We can actually go ahead and prove that using an assertion we're going to expect that user equals using
to equal the response.
Now this was not necessary for the challenge.
I'm going to be deleting this line in just a moment.
But over here you can see the test does indeed pass.
What I wanted you to do is check that the user object or the response object includes certain properties.
I'm going to check using expect that the result variable has some properties using to include the properties
I'm looking for are a first name equal to what I would expect that to be.
Andrew and a last name equal to meet.
Excellent.
And these are the assertions that should be made in order to verify that set name is working as expected.
If I saved the file the test suite reruns and we do indeed get the passing tests we have three of them
and it took just 10 milliseconds to run.
And with this in place we now have an assertion library for our test suite and that's fantastic because
writing test cases just got way easier and the whole goal of this section is to make testing approachable
and easy if testing is hard and painful you're not going to do it.
And I wouldn't blame you I wouldn't be testing either.
Hopefully by now though you're seeing that it doesn't need to be difficult.
It can be pretty awesome in the next video we're going to start looking at how we can test more complex
asynchronous functions.
That's coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.