In this video you're going to learn how to test asynchronous functions.
Before we get into that I want to make a quick note about the change in audio.
Unfortunately the microphone I've been using so far throughout the course has broken.
I've replaced it with a better one which is hopefully a lot crisper and clearer though you might need
to adjust your audio levels either up or down for it to sound just right.
Now I usually try not to update my gear in the middle of a correspond.
Fortunately I had no choice in this instance.
All right.
Now let's get down to testing.
Asynchronous functions.
The process of testing asynchronous functions isn't that different from synchronous ones like what we've
done already but it is a little different.
So it justifies its own video to get things off.
We're going to make a fake one using set time out to simulate a delay over inside of you tills.
J.S. just below where we make our add function.
I'm going to make one called Eysenck and it's essentially going to have the same features but it's going
to use set time out and it's going to have a callback to simulate a delay.
Now in the real world this delay might be a database request or an HTP request will be dealing with
that in the following sections.
For now though.
Module.
Exports dot async add.
This is going to take three arguments as opposed to the two the add function took a b and a callback.
And this is what's going to make the function asynchronous.
Eventually once the set time out is up we're going to call the call back with some whether it's one
plus three being four or five plus nine being 14.
Next up we can put the arrow in Arrow function and open and close our curly braces inside of here.
As I mentioned we're going to be using set time out to create that delay nothing new so far.
We'll pass in a callback and we'll pass in our time out.
I'm going to go with one second.
In this case no by default if your tests take longer than two seconds Moka is going to assume that is
not what you wanted and it's going to fail.
That's why I'm using one second.
In this case inside of our callback we can call the actual callback argument with some a plus b just
like this.
And there we go.
We now have an async add function and we can start writing a test for it.
Over inside of the utils test file just under our previous test for utility.
And I'm going to add a new one for async add in the test setup is going to look really similar.
We will be calling it and we will be passing in a string as the first argument and a call back as the
second it should a sync add two numbers.
Then we're going to add our call back just like this.
And inside of here we can get started calling you tills dot async ad I'm going to call it using you
tills async add and we're going to go ahead and pass in those three arguments I'll use four and three
which should result in seven.
And we'll provide the callback function which it should get called with that value the value being 7
right here inside of the callback arguments.
We would expect something like these some to come back.
Now we can start making some assertions about that some variable using expect we can pass it into expect
to make our assertions and these assertions aren't going to be new stuff.
We've already done.
I'm going to expect that these some equals using to be the number seven then I'm going to check that
it's a number using to be a inside of quotes number.
Now obviously if it is equal to 7 That means it is a number but I'm using both here just to simulate
exactly how chaining is going to work inside of your expect calls.
Now that we have our assertions in place let's go ahead and run our test and see what happens.
I'm going to run from the terminal NPM run test high and watch to start up our node man watching script
all of our tests run.
You can see right here we have three.
That's because I did not save the file yet.
I'm going to go ahead and save the file.
Now our tests are going to run and the test does indeed pass.
The only problem is that it's passing for the wrong reasons.
If I were to change seven to 10 and save the file the test is still going to pass.
Right here you see we have four Tests passing.
Now the reason this test is passing is not because the assertion right here is valid it's passing because
we have an asynchronous action that takes one second right here and this function is going to return
before the async callback gets fired.
But I say function returning.
I'm referring to this callback function.
The second argument to it and this is when Moka thinks your test is done.
This means that these assertions never run the Moka output has already set our test passes before this
callback ever gets fired.
What we need to do is tell Moka this is going to be an asynchronous test that's going to take time to
do this.
All we do is we provide an argument right here inside of the callback function we passed to it.
We're going to call this one done when you have the done argument specified.
Moka knows that means you have an asynchronous task and it's not going to finish processing this task
until done and gets called.
This means we can call done after our assertions with this in place.
Our test is now going to run the function will return right after it calls async add but that's OK because
we have done specified about a second later our callback function is going to fire inside of here we're
gonna make our assertions and this time the assertions will matter because we have done and we haven't
called it yet.
After the assertions we called done this tells Moka that we're all done with the test.
It can go ahead and process the result letting us know whether it passed or failed.
This is going to fix that error.
If I save the file in this state it's going to rerun the tests and we're going to see that our test
should async add two numbers is indeed going to fail over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to go ahead and open up the error message we have expected 7 to be 10 and this is exactly
what we thought would happen the first time around when we didn't use done.
But as we can see we do need to use done when we're doing something synchronous inside of our tests.
Now I can go ahead and change this expectation back to seven.
Save the file this time around.
Things should work as expected.
Notice that one second delay as it runs this test it can't report right away because it has to wait
for Don to get called down below.
Our total test time is now about a second.
You can see that right here we have four test passing Moka also warns you when a test takes a long time
because it assumes that's not expected.
Nothing inside of node even a database or HTP request should take even close to a second.
So it's essentially letting you know that there's probably an error somewhere inside of your function
it's taking a really really long time to process.
In our case though the one second delay was clearly set up inside of you tells So there's no need to
worry about that warning.
With this in place we now have a test for our very first asynchronous method.
All we had to do is add a done as an argument and call it once we were done making our assertions.
Now it's time for a challenge.
I want you to create an asynchronous version of the square method down below.
Go ahead and have it wait a second before calling the call back with de-value X times X then over inside
of the utility test file.
I want you to create a test that verifies the number that comes back is indeed the square in this case
you could pass in three and get nine back.
And I want to verify it's a number you're going to need to use done to get this done because it's going
to be an asynchronous function.
Go ahead and do the same thing for square that we just did for ADD.
When you're done you can go ahead and click play to go.
I hope you were able to create that sync function and write a test that verifies it works as expected
in order to get started.
I am going to define the function first and then we'll worry about writing that test over inside of
the file.
I can get started down below the square method of creating a new one called async square module.
Exports dot a sink Square.
It's going to take two arguments.
The original argument which we call it X and the callback function that's going to get called after
our one second delay.
And then I can finish up the arrow function and we can start working on the body of a sync Square.
It's going to look pretty similar to the async add one we'll call set time out passing in a callback
and a delay in this case the delay is going to be the same.
We'll go with one second.
Now we can go ahead and actually call the callback and this is going to trigger the callback function
that got passed in and we're going to pass in the value x times X which will properly square the number
passed in right here now over inside of the test file things are indeed passing.
But we haven't added a test for this function so let's go ahead and do that right now inside of you
tells test file the next thing you needed to do was call it down here.
I'm going to call it to make a new test for this async square function.
It should a sink square a number.
Perfect.
Next up we're going to provide the callback function that's going to get called when the test actually
executes.
And since we are testing in a sync function I'm going to put done right here.
This is going to tell Moka to wait until done is called to decide whether or not the test passed down
below.
We can now call you tills and Dot a sync square passing in a number of our choice.
I'm going to go ahead and use five.
Next up we can pass in a callback.
This is going to get the final result right here.
Well create a variable to store that result.
Now that we have this in place we can start making our assertions the assertions are going to be done
using the expect a library we're going to make some assertions about the response variable.
We're going to assert that it equals using to be the number 25 which is five times five.
And we'll also use to be a to assert something about the type of the value in this case we want to make
sure that the square is indeed a number as opposed to a boolean string or object.
With this in place I can now save the file.
But before I do I do need to call Don.
Remember if you don't call done your test is never going to finish.
You might find that every once in a while you're going to get an error like this over inside of the
terminal you're going to get an error.
Time out.
The two thousand milliseconds has exceeded.
And this is when Moka cuts off your test.
If you see this.
This usually means two things.
One you have an async function that never actually calls the callback.
So you call it a done it never gets fired or do you just never call it done.
In which case you can put done right here.
If you see this message it usually means there's a small typo somewhere in the async function.
Don't worry it's super easy to overcome.
Either fix things over in the method itself by making sure the callback is called or fix things over
in the test by calling Don and when you save the file you should not see all of your tests are passing.
Right here we have five tests passing and it took two seconds to do that.
This is fantastic.
We now have a way to test synchronous functions and asynchronous functions.
This is going to make testing a lot more flexible.
That's going to let us test essentially everything inside of our applications.
That is it for this one.
I will see you next time.
As we keep working through the different ways to test your node applications.
Up next we're going to look at how we can test our express apps