In this video you're going to be setting up an express app.
And in the next one we're going to look at how we can test it to verify that the data that comes back
from our routes is what the user should be getting.
Now before we do any of that we are going to need to create an express server and that's the goal of
this video.
Nothing new we've done it before.
I'm going to move through this pretty quickly since it's not new.
We're going to use NPM eye which is short for install to install Express.
Remember you could always replace install with AI.
And we're going to grab the most recent version at four point fourteen point zero and this time around
I'm going to be using the Save the flag as opposed to the save death flag that we've used for everything
in this section.
This is going to install express as a regular dependency which is exactly what we want we need express
when we deploy to production whether it's Heroku or some other service back inside of the app.
If I open up package.
Jason we now have dependencies which we've seen before and Deb dependencies which is new to this section.
This is how we can break up which dependency is which from here we're going to go ahead and make a server
folder inside of the root of the project where we can store the server example as well as the test file.
I'm going to make a directory called Server and then inside of here I'll make a file called you guessed
it Server dot Jay as the server digests file is going to contain the actual code that starts up our
server.
We're going to define our routes.
We're going to listen to a port all of that stuff is going to happen in here.
This is what we had before for the previous server.
S. Konst Express is going to get equal to the require Express return result.
Next up we can go ahead and make our application by creating a variable called app and setting it equal
to a call to express just like this.
Then we can start configuring our routes.
I'm going to go ahead and set up just one for this video app.
ADOT get this is going to set up an HTP get handler.
The u r l will be just forward slash the route of the website and when someone requests that for the
moment we're going to specify a really simple string as the return result.
We get the request and the response object like we do for all of our express routes and to respond.
We're going to call it response send sending back the string Hello world.
Excellent.
The last step in the process it's going to be to listen on a port using app ADOT listen I'm going to
bind to port three thousand by passing it and as the first and only argument with this in place we are
now done.
We have a basic express server before we move on to the next video and explore how to test these routes.
All I want to do is start it up.
I'm going to do that using node space server forward slash server.
Yes.
When I run this we don't get any logs because we haven't added a callback function for when the server
starts but it should indeed be up.
If I go over to Chrome and visit localhost three thousand.
Here we go.
We get hello world printing to the screen.
If you see this then you are done.
You are ready to move on to the next video where we are going to start testing our express application.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then