In this video you're going to learn an easy no nonsense way to test your express applications.
That means we can verify that when we make an HTP GET request to the following You are L..
We get the hello world response back.
Now traditionally testing HTP apps has been one of the more difficult things to test.
You would have to fire up a server like we do here.
Then you would need some code to actually make the request to the appropriate u r l and then you'd have
to dig through the response getting what you want and making assertions about it whether it's hetero's
the status code or the body or anything else.
It is a real burden and that is not the goal for this section.
The goal here is to make testing easy and approachable.
So we're going to use a library called super test to test our express applications super test was created
by the developers who originally created Express.
It has built in support for Express and it makes testing your express apps dead simple in order to get
started.
Let's go ahead and pull up the docs page so you know where it lives if you ever want to look at any
other features that it has to offer.
If you google super test it should be the first result.
It's the vision media repository and the repository itself is called Super Test.
I'm going to switch over to the repository page and we can take a quick look at what it has to offer.
Down below we can find installation instructions and introduction stuff.
We don't really need that.
Let's go ahead and take a quick look at an example right here.
We have an example of how super test works.
We created an express application just like we normally would and we define a route.
Then we make a call to the request method which is provided by super test passing in our express application.
We say we want to make a request of the following You are al.
Then we start making assertions right here.
There's no need to manually check either the headers the status code or the body.
It has a built in assertions for all of that to get started.
We're going to go ahead and install it in our application by running NPM install from the terminal.
I have my node server still running.
I'm going to shut that down and we can use NPM.
I if the module name is super test and we're going to be grabbing the most recent version at two point
zero point zero this is a task specific module so I'm not going to be installing it with save.
I'm going to use save dev to add it to my dev dependencies and package dot Jason with Super Test installed.
We are now ready to start filling out that server tasks.
JS file and now it doesn't yet exist inside of the server folder so we can go ahead and create it right
now.
It's going to sit just alongside.
Server dodginess server ADOT test dot.
J.S..
Awesome.
Now that we had this in place we can start setting up our very first test up at the very top I am going
to be creating a constant called request and setting that equal to the return result from requiring
super test.
And this is the main method we we're going to be using to test our express apps.
From here we can go ahead and load in the Express application.
Now inside of server G-S we don't have an export that exports the app.
So we're going to have to add that I'm going to add it down below by creating module exports dot app
and setting that equal to the app variable awesome.
And now we have an export called app that we can access from other files.
The server is still going to run as expected when we started from the terminal.
Not in test mode.
We just added an export.
So if anyone happens to require it they can get access to that app over inside of server tasks.
J.S..
I'm going to import this.
I'm going to make a variable.
I'm going to call the variable app.
Then we're going to go ahead and require using require
dot forward slash server J.S. or just server and then I'm going to access the dot app property.
Awesome.
With this in place we don't have everything we need to write our very first test.
The first test we're going to write is a test that verifies when we make an h t t p get request to the
following you R-AL we get.
Hello world back to do this.
We will be calling it just like we did for other tests.
We're still using Moka as the actual test framework.
We're using super test to fill in the gaps.
It should return hello world response perfect.
Now I'm going to set up my function.
This is going to be an asynchronous call so I will be providing done as the argument to let Moken know
to wait before determining whether or not the test passed or failed.
From here we can now make our very first call to request to use super test you call request passing
in the actual express application.
In this case we pass in the app variable then we can start chaining together all of the methods we need
to make the request make our assertions and finally wrap things up.
First up you're going to be using a method to actually make that request whether it's a get put delete
or a post.
We'll be talking about all of those in the next section when we create a full blown rest API.
For now we're going to be making a get request.
So we will use dot get don't get takes the U R L right here.
We'll provide forward slash just as we did over insurge Yes.
Next up that we can go ahead and make some assertions.
We've already made the request.
There's nothing more left to do to make assertions.
We're going to use dot expect no doubt expect is one of those methods that does different things depending
on what you pass to it.
In our case we'll be passing in a string.
I'm going to pass in this string which will be the response body that we assert.
Hello world.
With an exclamation mark at the end.
And now that we're done and we've made our assertions we can go ahead and wrap things up to wrap up
a request in super test.
All you do is you call DOT and passing in done as the callback.
This handles everything behind the scenes so you don't need to manually call done at a later point in
time.
All of it is handled by super test.
And with these four lines we have successfully tested our very first API requests.
I'm going to go ahead and kick things off over in the terminal by running our test watch script and
run test Python watch the test script is starting and right here we have some tests.
We have our test should return hello world response showing up right here.
Everything went great and this is fantastic.
Now we can take things a step further and making other assertions about the data that comes back.
For example I can go ahead and use expect right here to make an assertion about the status code by default
all of your express calls are going to return 200 status code which means that things went OK.
And if I saved the file the test still passes.
Now let's go ahead and make some changes to the request to make these tests.
They'll burst up in server.
Yes I'm just going to add a few characters to the string.
I'll add a few extra W's and I'll save the file.
This should cause these super test test to fail and it does indeed do that right here we get a message
we expected hello world response body.
But we got.
Hello world.
This is letting us know exactly what happened and back inside of the server.
Yes we can remove those extra W's and try something else.
Now we haven't talked about how to set a custom status for your response but we can do that with one
method.
Dot status just like this.
And we can change it on before send.
And we can pass in the numerical status code.
For example I could use a 404 for page not found if I saved the file this time around.
The body is going to match up but over in the terminal you can see we now have a different error.
We expected a 200 but we got a 4 0 for using super task.
We can make all sorts of assertions about our application.
Now the same thing is true for different types of responses.
For example I'm going to go ahead and create an object as the response let's make a simple object and
we'll create a property called error and we'll set error equal to a generic error message for a 4 or
4 something like page not found.
Now we're sending back a Jason body but currently we're not making any assertions about that body so
the test is going to fail.
We can go ahead and update our tests to expect Jason to come back in order to get that done.
All we have to do over inside of server test is change what we pass to expect instead of passing in
a string.
I'm going to go ahead and pass in an object.
Now we can match up that object exactly here.
I'm going to go ahead and expect that the error property exists and that it equals exactly what we have
here.
Page Not Found capital-T page not found with a period at the end.
With this in place our assertions now match up with the actual endpoint we've defined over inside of
the Express application.
I should be able to save the file and watch all my tests pass over in the terminal.
You can see we are still getting an error.
We expected a 200 but got a 4 or 4.
I forgot to tweak that.
So I will change this expect call to a 404.
Now this should cause a new refresh of the tests and this time everything should be passing.
If I scroll down you can see it is indeed passing should return hello world response is passing.
It took about 41 milliseconds to complete and that is perfectly fine.
Well a lot of the built in assertions do get the job done for the majority of cases there are times
where you want a little more flexibility.
For example we just learned about all those cool assertions I expect can make.
We can use to include to exclude all of that stuff is really handy and it's a shame to lose it.
Well luckily there's a lot of flexibility with super test what we can do instead of taking an object
and passing it into aspect or a number for the status code.
We can go ahead and provide a function.
This function is going to get called by super test and it's going to get past the response.
This means we can access headers abody anything we want to access from the HTP response is going to
be available right here and we can pipe it through the regular expect assertion library like we've been
doing before.
I'm going to go ahead and load it in creating a constant called expect in sending an equal to require
expect.
Awesome.
Now before we look at how it's going to work we're going to go ahead and make a change in server dot
J.S..
What I want to do is add a second property on to here.
I'm going to add an error and then I'll add something else.
I'm going to go ahead and use name setting equal to the application name to do app the one at point
zero.
Now that we have this in place we can take a look at how we can use those custom assertions over inside
of our test file right here.
We're going to have access to the response and on the response there is a body property like we've seen
in the past.
This is going to be a javascript object with key value pairs which means we would expect to have an
error property and a name property which we set right here back inside of our test file.
We can make a custom assertion using expect I'm going to expect something about the body response dot
body.
Now I can go ahead and use any assertion I like not just the equals assertion which is the only one
super test supports.
I'm going to go ahead and use that to include assertion.
Remember to include lets you specify a subset of the properties on the object as long as it has those
ones that's fine.
It doesn't matter that it has extra ones.
In our case we can go ahead and inside of to include just specify the error message leaving off the
fact that name exists at all.
I want to check that error equals page not found formatted exactly like we have it over inside of server.
Yes now when I go ahead and save the file back inside of the terminal things restart and all of my tests
are passing.
This is fantastic.
Using a combination of super test and expect we can have super flexible test suites for our HTP endpoints.
With this in place it is now time for a challenge where you're going to create your very own express
route and you're going to define a test that makes sure it works as expected.
There's going to be two sides to this.
The actual set up in Cervidae.
Yes and the test.
We can start inside of server.
Yes down here.
You're gonna make a new route.
I'll leave a few comments to specify exactly what I'd like.
It's going to be an HTP get route the route itself will be forward slash users and we can just assume
this returns an array of users.
You can pass an array back through the send method just like we do an object here.
Now this array is going to be an array of objects where each object is a user.
For now I want you to give users give users a name property and an age prompt.
Go ahead and create two or three users for this example.
You can just add yourself and out some of your friends putting in the first name and the age as props.
Now once you have this done you're going to be responsible for writing a test that asserts it works
as expected.
That's going to happen over in server dot test dot.
J.S. down below.
You're going to make a new test make a new test and this test is going to assert a couple of things.
First up I want you to assert that the status code that comes back is a two hundred assert 200 and I
want to make an assertion that inside of that array your user object exists and you're going to do that
using to include assert that you exist in user's array.
Now it's perfectly fine if there are other users I've told you to add them.
What's really important though is that you just test that your user exists and object in the array with
the first name equal to whatever you set.
That's the name Propp and the age equal to whatever you set as well.
Once that's in place go ahead and run the test suite.
Make sure your new test is passing.
If it is fantastic you are done.
You can go ahead and click play.
Take a moment.
Knock that out and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you are able to make not only the end point but also the test using super test.
I'm going to define the end point first over inside of server dot J.S. just above the comments I'll
call app get so we can register the brand new HTP endpoint for our application and this one is going
to be at forward slash users.
Next up we're going to specify the callback that takes both request and response.
This is going to let us actually respond to the request and the goal here was just to respond with an
array.
In this case I'm going to call response and send passing in an array of objects.
The first object will be someone else.
I'll set the name equal to my friend Mike's name and we'll set his age equal to 27.
Then I can add another one.
This one will be me.
I'm going to add the second object to the array with a name equal to Andrew and an age equal to 25 and
the last one will do I'll set the name equal to Jan and the age equal to twenty six.
Perfect.
Now obviously we're using static data here but in the next section we're going to start creating a real
API with real data.
So it's important to learn how to test with static data so we don't have to learn two things at the
same time.
Now that we have our endpoint done we can go ahead and save server dot us move into server dot test
dot J us and start worrying about actually creating our test case just below the comments you needed
to start things out by calling it.
It is the only way to make a new test.
It should return my user object.
Then I'm going to go ahead and specify the callback function.
It is going to get past that done argument because remember this one is going to be a synchronous to
kick things off inside of the test case.
I will be calling a request just like we did up above passing in the Express application and now we
can go ahead and set up the actual call.
In this case we're just making a call a get request to the following.
You are all inside of quotes.
Forward slash users.
Next up we can start making our assertions and the first thing you supposed to assert is that the status
code is a 200 which is the default status code used by express.
I can assert that by calling and expect and passing in the status code as a number in this case I'll
pass in at 200 after this.
I want you to use a custom expect assertion.
This means that you're going to call expect passing in a function and you're going to use to include
inside of it to make the assertion that you exist in that user's array.
I'm going to call.
Expect the method passing in the function and that function will get called with the response.
This is going to let us make some assertions about the response what we're actually going to do is make
an assertion using expect we're going to expect something about the response body in this case.
We'll be checking that it includes using to include our user object.
Now remember you can call to include on both arrays and objects.
We've used the object one here.
We have used the array one previously but we'll use it again right now.
All we do is pass and the item we want to confirm is in the array.
In our case it's an object where the name property equals Andrew.
Use your name there and the age property equals whatever age you put.
I'm going to go ahead and put 2005 which is what I use over inside a server Dhananjay.
Yes.
Now that we have our customers expect call in place at the very bottom we can call DOT and this is going
to wrap up the request and we can go ahead and pass in Dunhams the callback so we can properly fire
off those errors if any actually occurred.
And with this in place we are ready to get going.
I'm going to go ahead and save the file over inside of the terminal.
You can see the tests are indeed rerunning.
We have a test right here.
Should return my user object.
It is passing.
That is fantastic.
Now we can confirm that we're not going crazy and testing the wrong thing by just messing up the data.
If I add a lowercase after the uppercase one in Andrew the test fails you can see that over in the terminal
and this is fantastic.
And now we have testing for our express apps.
Now we will be using Express extensively in the next couple of sections.
For now though we're going to talk about one more way we can test our node code that is coming up next
so stay tuned.
I will see you then.