In this video you are going to learn how to use describe described as a function injected into your
test files just like it is.
It comes from a moka and it's really fantastic.
Essentially it lets you group tasks together.
That makes it a lot easier to scan the test output.
If I run our NPM test command in the terminal I can show you what I'm talking about.
Right here we get our tests.
We have seven tests and currently they're all grouped together.
It's really hard to look for the tests in the Eutelsat file and it's impossible to find the tests for
async add without scanning all of the text.
But we're going to do is call describe this is going to let us make groups of tasks we can give that
group a name.
It's going to make our test output much much more readable.
Right here I'm going to go ahead and call describe describe that takes two arguments just like it.
The first one is the name I'm going to go ahead and use utilities.
This is going to be describe a block that contains all of the tasks in the utility test file.
Then I'm going to provide my function.
This is the callback function inside of this function.
We're going to be defining tests.
Any test defined in here is going to be part of the utils block.
That means we can take our existing tests cut them out of the file paste them in there and we'll have
a describe block called you tails with all of the tests for this file down below.
I'm going to do just that.
I'm going to grab all of the tests excluding the ones that are just playground tests where we'd play
around with various xpect functionality and I'm going to paste them right in here.
This is for one for ADD async add square and a sink Square.
Now I'm going to save the file and we can start up the test watch script from the terminal and we can
check out the output NPM run test hyphen watch.
The script starts it's going to run through our tests and right here we now have different output.
We have a utility section and under you tells indented two spaces.
We have all of the tasks in it that describe black.
This makes reading and scanning your tests much much easier.
We can go ahead and do the same thing for the individual methods.
Now in this case we have one test per method.
But if you have a lot of tests that are targeting a complex method it's best to wrap that in its own
described block.
We can just describe blocks and tests in any way we like.
For example right here inside of you taels I can call describe again we can pass a new description I'm
going to go ahead and use pound sign followed by ADD.
This is the common syntax for adding a describe block for a specific method pound sign followed by the
method name.
And then I can go ahead and provide that callback function.
And I can take any tests I want to add into that group cut them out and paste them in and then I can
go ahead and save the file.
This is going to rerun the test suite and now we have test output that's even more scannable.
It's super easy to find the tails add method tests because they're clearly labeled.
Now you could go as crazy or has an crazy with this as you want.
There really is no hard and fast rule for how often to use describe a your tests.
It's really up to you to figure out what makes sense given the amount of tests you have for a method
or a file.
In this case we have quite a few tests in the file so it definitely makes sense to add that you tell
us.
BLOCK And I just wanted to show you when you could nest them so I added it for ADD as well.
If I was writing this code I probably wouldn't add a second layer of tests but if I had more than one
test per method I definitely would add a second to describe block.
Now that we have this in place I want you to create some undescribed blocks of your own.
Over in the server test file right here I'll show you exactly what I want you to do.
We're going to create a route.
Describe block called server.
Then you're going to create describe blocks for both the route you are l and for forward slash users.
We'll have to get forward slash.
That's going to have the test case in there some test case then alongside of forward slash we're going
to have you get bored slash users and that's going to have its own test case some test case.
Now the test cases are obviously already defined below.
All you need to do is call describe three times to generate the structure put the text here in the string
for the description and then you'll be done.
So take a moment to knock that out call the scribe three times and each test into the appropriate describe
callback function.
When you're done go ahead and save the file to rerun it from the terminal and make sure everything shows
up as it should.
All right.
Hopefully you were able to call describe three times creating the structure we have here.
I'm going to call describe once right here and this description is going to be for the route.
So I'm going to call this one server.
This is going to contain all of the tasks in our server file.
I can add my callback and we can move on.
Next up I am going to call the scribe again.
This time we're creating a describe a block for tests that test the get forward slash route.
I'm going to add the callback function and now we can simply take our test and copy it inside.
I'm going to cut it out.
And paste it right inside of the describe callback add some semi-colons and we are on our way.
Next up we're going to go ahead and remove these comments since they're no longer needed and we can
call describe the third time right here.
We're going to be calling described passing in as the description we get forward slash users.
We're going to have our callback function as always.
And then we can copy and paste our test right inside.
I'm going to grab the final test cut it out and move it inside.
Awesome.
With this in place we are now done the challenge.
We have a much better structure for our tasks.
And when we rerun the test suite by saving the file we'll be able to see that over in the terminal right
here.
We have a much more scannable test suite.
We can see our server tests right away.
We can create groups of tests for each feature since we have static data.
Right now we really don't need more than one test per feature but down the line we will have multiple
tests for each of our HTP requests.
So it's a good idea to get into that habit of creating describe blocks early and that's it for this
one.
The next video is the last one for this section.
We'll explore one more way we can test our node applications.
Then we'll continue on creating real world projects and actually putting this testing in to practice.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.