In this video which is the final video for the testing section you're going to learn some pretty advanced
testing techniques we'll be using this throughout the rest of these sections as we build real world
apps.
But for now I want to start off with an example.
We'll worry about the vocabulary for what I'm about to do in just a second.
For the moment all I want you to do is close all your files and create a new directory in the root of
the project right here.
I'm going to make a new folder called spies.
We'll talk about what exactly spies are and how they relate to testing in just a moment.
Inside of spies we're going to make two files after us.
This is the file that will be testing and a second one called D-B Scott J.S. in our example we can just
assume that this is a file that has all sorts of methods for saving and reading data from the database
inside of DVDs.
Yes.
We're going to create one function using module dot exports.
I'm going to create a function called Save user save user is going to be a really simple function.
It's going to take a user object and we're just going to go ahead and print it to the screen using console
lock.
I'm going to print a little message saving the user.
And I'll also print out the object right here.
Now obviously this is not a real save user function.
We do not interact with any sort of database but it is going to illustrate exactly how we're going to
be using spies to test our code.
Next up we're going to fill out apps.
Yes.
And this is the file We're actually going to be testing inside of Apple.
We're going to create a new function module.
Exports a dock handle Sign-Up in the context of an application with authentication handle sign up might
take an e-mail and a password maybe it goes ahead and checks if the e-mail already exists.
If it doesn't great.
It saves the user and then it sends some sort of welcome.
Now we can go ahead and simulate that by creating an aero function that takes an e-mail and a password
inside of here we're going to leave three comments.
These will be things that the function is supposed to do is going to check if the email already exists.
It's going to save the user to the database.
And finally we're going to send that welcome email
perfect.
Now these three things are just an example of what a handle sign up method might actually do.
Let me go through the real process you'll see how it pans out.
Now we already have one of these in place we just created save user.
So what I'm going to do is go ahead and call save user instead of having the second comment right here.
I'm going to call it D-B dot save user.
It's not imported just yet.
But that's not going to stop us from calling it will add the import in just a second and I'm going to
pass in what it expects the user object.
Now I don't have a user object.
I have an e-mail and a password.
I can create a user object by sending email equal to the e-mail argument and setting password equal
to the password argument just like this.
Excellent.
Now one important thing to note inside of 6 if the property name on an object you're setting is the
same as a variable name you can actually define it like this.
In this example since I'm sending it password property and I'm setting it equal to whatever's on the
password variable there's no need to have both.
This ios six syntax also allows us to create a much simpler looking call.
There's no need to have it on multiple lines since it's pretty reasonable in length.
Awesome.
Now we can load NDB by creating a variable calling it DBI and setting it equal to require DBI dot Jap's.
That is a local file so we're going to start it with a dot forwards slash to grab it from the current
directory.
Now this is an example of something that we're going to want to test inside of our code.
We have a handle Sign-Up method it takes an e-mail and a password and we need to make sure that DBT
save user works as well.
That is a big problem.
And this means that we're not just testing handle sign up we're testing handle sign up we're testing
our code that checks if an email exists.
Maybe that is another function or checking if the safe user function works as expected.
We're checking if the welcome email sends that is a real pain but we're going to do instead is fake
this function.
It's never actually going to execute the code inside of here but it is going to let us verify that when
we run handle Sign-Up save user gets called we're going to do this with something called spies.
Spies let you swap out a real function like save user for a testing utility.
When that test function gets called you can create various assertions about it making sure it was called
with certain arguments.
Let's go ahead and start exploring that right here.
I'm going to make a new file called app dot test dot J.S. and we can start playing around with spies
now spies do come built in with expect.
So all we have to do is loaded in Konst expect equals require expect and from here we can create our
very first test.
I'm going to go ahead and put this in a describe block so it's easier to find over in our test output.
I'll call this describe a block app and I'll add my callback function.
And now I can add my individual test cases.
First up we're going to call it and we're going to make a new test where we can just play around with
spies.
We won't be calling the function in our apt.
Jazz file just yet.
It should call this spy correctly in order to visualize how spies work.
We're going to go through the most basic example we can.
First up creating a spy to create a spy.
You're going to call a function expect dot create spy create spy is going to return a function and that
is the function that you're going to swap out for the real one which means we do want to store that
in a variable.
I'm going to create a variable called Spy setting equal to the return result.
And now we would inject spy into our code whether it's app dot J.S. or some other function and we would
wait for it to get called We Can Go ahead and call it directly right here.
I'm going to call spy just like this.
Next up we can set up a series of assertions using expects spies assertions.
If you head over to your browser and go to the expect documentation and Jackson expect I have it right
here.
We can scroll down to the spies section where they talk about all of the assertion you have access to.
It's pretty far down on the page.
You should start seeing spies in the method names and that's when you know you've gotten there right
below to include and to exclude keys.
I have to have been called this is our first assertion with spies.
We can assert that our spy was indeed called over inside an atom.
We're going to go ahead and do that by calling expect and passing in the spy just like this.
Then I'm going to add the assertion to have been called and this is going to cause the test to pass.
If SPY was called What It Was and it'll cause the test to fail.
If the spy was never called I can run to the test suite inside of the terminal using NPM run test hyphen
watch.
And this is going to kick off the tests using node Mon.
Right here we have all of our test cases.
And under the app one we have should call the spy correctly it did indeed pass which is fantastic.
Now let's go ahead and comment out the line where I call spy and this time around the test should fail
because the spy was never actually called and right here we see spy was not called.
No checking if a spy was called or not called is great but we can get even more detail out of our assertions
for example what if I call the spy with the name Andrew and the age 25 and I want to verify that the
spy was not just called but was called with these arguments.
Well luckily we have an assertion for that to instead have to have been called we can call it to have
been called with this lets us pass in some arguments and verify the spy was indeed called with those
arguments right here.
I'm going to assert that my spy was called with Andrew and the number 25 when I saved the file in the
test cases restart.
I should see all my tests passing and that's exactly what I get.
Now if the spy was not called with this data I'm going to go ahead and remove 25 and we rerun the test
suite.
The test is going to fail.
It's going to give you an error message letting you know that the spy was never called with Andrew and
25 this is causing the test to fail which is fantastic.
Now there are plenty of other assertions we can use with our spies you can find them over in the expect
docs.
We have to have been called which we used to not have been called verifying that a spy was not called
then we have to have been called with which we also used Double-O.
You can see there's a lot more to spies as well.
How to create spies which we've already done and a few other methods which are not going to explore
now although they could be useful in the future for our purposes.
We need a spy so we can simulate that function inside of apts.
J.S. save user We need a way to replace this function with a spy.
Then we can verify that and handle sign up gets called.
It does indeed call save user.
It doesn't need to actually go through the process over NDB dot jazz.
This is not important to our tests.
The only thing that is important is that the function was called with the correct arguments to do that.
We're going to look at an NPM module called rewire which lets us swap out variables for our tests.
In our case in our test file we'll be able to replace the DBI object with something else completely.
Then when the code runs instead of calling DB save user as defined over here it's going to be calling
D-B dot save user which will be a spy to get started.
We do need to install rewire over in the terminal.
It's a fantastic test utility.
It's pretty essential for testing functions with side effects like the one we have here.
I'm going to run NPM install the module name itself is called rewire and we're going to be grabbing
the most recent version as of this filming version two point five point two.
This is a test specific module.
We're not going to need it for our application to run regularly.
So we will be using the saved flag to add it to our package.
Jason dependencies list once the module is installed we can get started using it and it's pretty simple
to set up over inside of app test.
Scott J.S. we can start by loading it in up at the very top.
I'm going to create a new constant.
This one will be called a rewire.
And we're going to set it equal to the return result from requiring re wire.
Now the way that rewire works is it requires you to use rewire instead of require when you're loading
in the file that you want to mark out.
For this example we want to replace it with something else.
So when we load an app we have to load it in a special way.
I'm going to make a variable called app and we're going to set it equal to rewire followed by what we
would usually put inside of a choir in this case it's a relative file a file that we created daat forward
slash app is going to get the job done.
Now rewire load your file through require but it also adds to methods on to app.
These methods are app dot underscore underscore set underscore underscore and app dot underscore underscore
get dot underscore underscore we can use these to mock out various data inside of app.
Yes that means we're going to make a simulation of the D-B object to the one that comes back from DBD.
Yes but we'll swap out the function with ASPI inside of our descry block we can kick things off by making
a variable this variable is going to be called D.B and we're going to set it equal to an object.
The only thing we need to mark out in our case is save user right here.
I'm going to define save user then I'm going to go ahead and said equal to a spy by creating one using
expect dot create spy just like we did down below.
And now we have this D-B variable.
And the only thing left to do is replace it.
And we do that using app dot underscore underscore set underscore underscore and this takes two arguments.
The first one is the thing you want to replace were trying to replace D-B and we're trying to replace
it with the D variable which is an object that has the same user function just like we have over here
without emplace we can now write a test that verifies that handle sign up does indeed call save user
Double-O.
I'm going to call it.
It should call save user with user object.
Then we can pass in our function and this is what's going to actually run when the test gets executed
and there's no need to use any asynchronous done arguments.
This is going to be a synchronous test.
For now inside of here we can come up with an e-mail and a password that will pass in to handle sign
up right here.
I'm going to make a variable called e-mail sending it equal to some e-mail Andrew at example dot com
and we can do the same thing with a password var password.
I'll set that equal to 1 to 3 a b c.
Next up we are going to call handle Sign-Up This is the function we want to test.
I'm going to call app dot handle Sign-Up passing in our two arguments email and password.
Now at this point handle sign up is going to get executed.
That means the code over here is going to run and it's going to fire D-B data save user but D-B don't
save user is not the method in NDB.
Yes it's a spy instead which means we can now use those assertions.
We just learned about right here inside of the test case.
I'm going to use expect to expect something about D-B the variable right here.
Dot save user which we set equal to a spy.
I'm going to call DOT to have been called with and I'm going to call this with an object because that
is what DVDA us should have been called with.
We'll use that same as 6 shortcut e-mail Khama password.
This creates an email attribute set to the e-mail variable and a password attribute set to the password
variable.
With this in place we can now save our test file and over in the terminal I can restart the task watch
script by using the up arrow key twice to rerun our NPM run test watch command.
This is going to kick off our test suite starting up all of our tests and right here we see should have
called the spy correctly fails.
That's because we had previously messed up the test case to make sure it failed.
I'm going to add that back but that's not important because the test case we did just create that did
indeed pass should call a save user with the user object.
And this is fantastic.
We don't have a way to test pretty much anything inside of Node.
We can even test functions that call other functions and verifying that the communication happens as
expected.
And all of this can be done using spies.
And now I understand that the concepts in this video in particular can be a little hard to grasp especially
when you're not using it in the context of a real application.
And that's why we are done with a testing section and we're going to move on creating real world apps.
Most notably we're going to create a to do rest API and we're going to make a real time application
with sockets that is all coming up next and we will be using testing throughout the rest of the course.
I am super excited to get to it so I will see you next time as we start building our rest API